[Music]
[Musique]
m
m
no
non
the
le
[Music]
[Musique]
we're going to move on to the Cypriot news
on va embrayer sur l'actualité chypriote
Olivier Delamarche what
olivier delamarche qu'est ce que vous
can you tell us about the situation in
pouvez nous dire sur la situation de
Cyprus the astonishing, the side effects without the
chypre l'étonnant les à côtés sans les
mechanisms played by
mécanismes a joué par
Roger or not we were told it was over that it was
roger ou pas on nous a dit que c'était
settled but I have
fini que c'était réglé moi j'ai
the impression that it's not at all we'll talk about it again soon we saw
l'impression que ça n'est pas du tout on
that it was managed in the
bien vu quand même que ça a été géré la
stupidest way possible
façon la plus stupide qui soit
we closed the Cypriot banks in
on a fermé les banques chypriotes à
Cyprus but we forgot to close them in
chypre mais on a oublié de les fermer à
London and as a result you have a good
londres et résultat vous avez une bonne
part of the funds that have been exfiltrated
partie des fonds qui ont été exfiltrés
from the banks so as a
des banques donc
result we'll realize in a
résultat on va s'apercevoir dans
few days or a few weeks that
quelques jours ou quelques semaines que
the 6 billion we were supposed to recover
les 6 milliards qu'on devait récupérer
are not there and at that point we'll have to start all over again so as
sont pas là et à ce moment là il faudra
usual as was done in
tout recommencer donc comme d'habitude
Greece as has been done
comme qui a été fait en grèce comme ce
every time it was done
qui a été fait à chaque fois ça a été
in spite  Common sense dictates that we
fait en dépit du bon sens et donc
do things wrong, as usual,
on fait les choses mal comme d'habitude
and that results in the problem
et donc ça aboutit à ce que le problème
not being solved at all, and that we talk about it
soit pas du tout régler et que on en
week after week for
reparle semaine après semaine pendant
months and months and months and months,
des mois et des mois et des mois et des
and that in a few months, one by one, we will arrive at a
mois et que donc on va arriver dans
problem like that of
problème qui sera qui sera comme celui
Greece, with unfortunately
de la grèce avec malheureusement des
signals that have been given that will
signaux qui ont été données qui vont
trigger,
déclencher pour moi
I think, a bank run in weak countries,
je pense un bank run dans les pays
including France. Let's
dont la france un neveu ne nous excluons
not exclude ourselves from these countries. Let's say a
pas de ces pays là g admettons qu'un
country leaves the European Union. The
pays sorte de l'union européenne
country that has the euro will find itself
le pays qui a aisni les 06 et euro se
in other
retrouvent dans d'autres banques
central banks because these euros will become
centrales parce que ces euro deviendront
toxic assets. Well, yes,
des actifs toxiques
obviously, that will pose a serious
bah oui évidemment ça va poser une grave
difficulty because
une grave difficulté parce que
currently no process for
actuellement aucun processus de sortie
a country to leave the Eurozone exists. We
d'un pays de la zone euro n'existe on
even see that in the texts, the rules, it probably serves
voit même que dans les textes les canons
to
sa sert a sans doute pour sortir l'euro
leave the European Union. We
faut sortir de l'union européenne on
see that we are still very far
voit qu'on est quand même très loin
from having flexible management at this level,
d'avoir une gestion souple à ce niveau
and I take it very seriously.  It's not entirely out of the question that Cyprus will be
là et j'y prends pas tout à fait exclue
one of the first countries where
que ce soit un des premiers pays sur
an experiment to
lequel on tentera une expérimentation de
exit the Eurozone will be attempted, with
sortie de la zone euro ayant même
the International
l'association internationale des
Bankers Association even pushing somewhat in this
banquiers pousse un peu dans cette seule
direction. The difficulty,
dans cette voie là la difficulté
of course, lies in the situation in
évidemment et que sur la situation à
Cyprus, where a
chypre un
Western perspective has led to debts three to four times
moment d'occidental a fait trois quatre
greater than what can
fois plus des dettes que ce qui ne
probably ever be repaid.
pourra probablement jamais remboursé
Since 2008, there has been a beginning of a return to
depuis 2008 on a un début de retour à la
reality, but we are still in a
réalité mais on est toujours dans une
situation where lenders
situation où les prêteurs pense
obviously think they will be repaid, and
évidemment qu'ils seront remboursés et
borrowers think that
les emprunteurs pense que de toute façon
they will never be able to repay, or at least that they won't be able to cope. They are resorting to
ils ne pourront jamais rembourser ou en
raising massive
nom pas faire face et de lever massives
taxes in the short term, taxes which,
d'impôts à court terme impôts qui est de
if raised, would be
toute façon si on les levait serait
extremely destructive to
extrêmement destructeur pour voir
the economy.
l'économie
Cyprus is the first country where
chypre est le premier pays sur lesquels
we are seeing a beginning of a return to reality, which
on a un début de retour à la réalité qui
is that all its losses,
est que toutes ses pertes
currently its accountant,
eric actuellement son comptable vols
are being remitted to the public.
sont en train d'être redescendu vers les
So,
arts les personnes physiques donc
obviously, Cyprus hasn't had
évidemment chypre n'a pas eu cette fois
two dead plans this time.  impacting its
deux plans dead pour ne pas impacter sa
population, as Greece or
population comme a eu la grèce ou comme
other countries have experienced, these plans have
ont eu d'autres pays ces plans ayant
always been financed by
toujours été financée par de la dette
additional debt. So in Cyprus, in Asia, they
supplémentaire donc à chypre en asie on
no longer want to take on debt, and since they no longer
ne veut plus faire de dette et donc
want to take on debt, the
comme on veut plus faire de dettes le
system is bankrupt. And so,
système est en faillite et donc voilà
everyone involved will take their losses,
chacun intervenant va prendre ses pertes
obviously the bank shareholders first,
évidemment les actionnaires des banques
then the
en premier lieu puis les prêteurs
bank bond lenders (there aren't
obligataires des banques y en a pas
many in Cyprus), obviously the very
beaucoup à chypre évidemment les très
large depositors, and it's not guaranteed
gros déposants puis ce n'est pas garanti
beyond one hundred thousand euros.
au delà de cent mille euros
So yes, Cyprus is a
donc oui à chypre et en est un
small laboratory for this. Indeed, it's
un petit laboratoire alors effectivement
extremely unpleasant for the
extrêmement déplaisant pour la
population, and no, it's catastrophic
population et non c'est catastrophique
what's happening in Cyprus.
ce qui se passe à chypre en train de
Most companies are brooding because,
ruminer la plupart des entreprises parce
obviously, their cash flow is being depleted in the
qu'évidemment leur trésorerie est amputé
same way, plus, let's say at
la même façon plus les on va dire au
least, the medium to very large depositors.
moins les déposants moyen à très gros de
Unfortunately, what else can we
lille malheureusement c'est que peut-on
do in this situation,
faire d'autre dans cette situation
Bernard? Yes, just one word: it's a very
bernard oui juste juste un mot c'est un
small problem, it's a problem. And
tout petit problème c'est un problème et
if the SKC Pinacci  Prince and 0.05
si le skc pinacci prince et 0,05 pour
percent of European wealth, the
cent de la richesse européenne du pnd
European GDP simply raises the question of our
européen simplement ça pose après nos
principles in the event of an exit, which is that of expansion, like an
principes en cas de sortie qui est celui
oil slick.
de l'extension lalanne en tache d'huile
Those of the two consequences of this
ceux des deux des conséquences de cette
exit vis-à-vis other states would be
sortie vis-à-vis d'autres états alors eu
much more significant in terms of
beaucoup plus significatif en terme de
shares in European wealth, but above all,
parts dans la richesse européenne mais
the Cyprus story
surtout surtout l'histoire de chypre
demonstrates once again that we built
démontre une fois de plus on a construit
the euro by going against
l'euro en allant vers si vous dira à
common sense. We brought together
l'encontre du bon sens on a mis ensemble
a number of completely
un certain nombre de pays complètement
heterogeneous countries economically, countries that had
hétérogène sur le plan économique qui
not reached the same
n'avait pas atteint le stade le même
stage of maturity, and we created a
stade de maturité et on a créé une
single currency
monnaie unique entre une monnaie unique
between them. The result is that, indeed,
entre eux le résultat c'est
a number of
qu'effectivement un certain nombre de
countries are not capable of respecting
pays ne sont pas capables de respecter
the discipline that results from this
la discipline qui résulte de cette
currency, especially when it was
monnaie ait surtout quand elle a été
raised by
levée vers le haut par la la la position
Germany's position. In fact, what should have been
de l'allemagne en fait ce qu'il aurait
done—it's obvious now,
fallu faire c'est évident maintenant
but some have said it before—
mais certains l'ont dit écrire avant
is to wait until there was a minimum
c'est attendre qu'ils aient un minimum
of economic coherence between the
de cohérence économique entre les
nations, and then how to bring
nations puis là comment faire entrer
nations into the euro.  Having the same
dans l'euro des nations ayant le même
economic status, the same
statut économique la même cohérence
economic coherence, the same economic wealth,
économique la même richesse économique
is that what you think? Do you
est ce que vous pensez est-ce que vous
think that Germany pushed for
pensez que l'allemagne a poussé deux
weaker countries to join so
pour faire entrer des pays faibles pour
that the euro would have a weaker value? It's
que l'euro est une valeur moins forte
easy to see why, given its exports. I don't
facile quand ses exportations je ne
think so. I think Germany
pense pas je pense que l'allemagne
has always supported a
a toujours soutenu une politique de
strong currency policy, both during the Deutsche
monnaie forte à l'époque du deutsche
Mark era and now with the euro.
mark et maintenant à l'époque de l'euro
The euro is, in a way, a
l'euro étant en quelque sorte pour les
substitute for the Deutsche Mark for
allemands le succédané de douche marque
the Germans, so they are
pour que les allemands se satisfont
perfectly content with a
parfaitement d'une madness si tu vois un
high level compared to other
niveau élevé par rapport aux autres
major international currencies.
grandes monnaies internationales
So they aren't looking for a decline at all.
donc ils ne cherchent pas du tout à la
Through this kind of phenomenon,
baisse-- par ce genre de phénomène en
they have been caught in a kind of
fait ils ont été pris dans un espèce de
trap, which I call infernal,
de pièges que j'appelle infernale pour
by which, moreover,
ma part par lequel le sens d'ailleurs
the European peoples don't
que les peuples européens le sache ne le
know the meaning of the same thing. We created,
sache les le sens de même on a créé en
being very dense, and led with
étant très dense est mené avec dédé des
components of states
composantes des composants des états
that had no
qu'ils n'avaient aucune homogénéité
economic homogeneity, so all of this couldn't
économique donc tout ça ne pouvait pas
hold up. All of this was going to explode one day.
tenir tout ça venait à éclater un jour
Your interpretation of those who would have the
votre lecture de ceux qui auraient la
capacity to act, that is to say, Brussels, the
capacité d'agir c'est à dire le brussels
leaders, the main
les dirigeants les principaux dirigeants
European leaders, does their capacity
européens est ce que leur capacité
for action seem realistic to you given
d'action vous semble réaliste face à
the scale of the problem? The only way to
l'ampleur du problème la seule façon de
allow marginal states, if I may
permettre aux états marginaux si j'ose
say so economically, within the euro, the only
dire économiquement dans l'euro la seule
way to allow them to stay in
façon de leur permettent de tenir dans
the euro, would be to lower the value of
l'euro ce serait d'abaisser la valeur de
the euro against others, as in other countries, to carry out
l'euro contre les autres comme dans les
a devaluation, said
autres me faire une dévaluation a dit
Boudreau, conquered, and in relation to the dollar,
boudreau conquis et de rapport au dollar
for example, from 1.20 to 25, which all
par exemple de 1 20 à 25 que tous les
economists have in mind and which, moreover, respects these
économistes ont en tête et qui respecte
economic and financial ratios. But
économiques mais et financier mais
how did you arrive at this? I don't believe that it is
comment t'est arrivé je ne crois pas que
the action of states that will
ce soit l'action des états qu'il
allow the situation, and the law is the law
permettra au ca et la loi c'est la loi
of supply and demand that regulates
de l'offre et de la demande qui régule
the parity of currencies every day, and once again, this is
tous les jours la parité des monnaies et
the euro, and to a
encore une fois ce l'euro et dans une
large extent influenced by the
large mesure influencé par la santé
still brilliant health of Germany today,
éclatante encore aujourd'hui de
Olivier, with the expectations in
l'allemagne olivier avec les attentes en
terms of 2, how to say  of growth or
terme de 2 comment dire de croissance ou
freeing it to Germany, is it if we only
libériez il à l'allemagne est elle si on
train that, no, no, it's certain that
forme que ça non non c'est sûr que
Germany wasn't going to, yes, compared
l'allemagne allait pas oui par rapport
to others today, it is, it is doing
aux autres aujourd'hui elle et elle va
better,
elle va mieux
the question is obviously when the
la question c'est évidemment quand la
recession will spread to the other
récession va gagner les autres pays aux
surrounding countries which are its main
alentours qui sont ses principaux
customers, obviously it will go badly,
clients évidemment qu'elle ira l'ira mal
its model is extremely
son modèle est extrêmement
unbalanced, in fact extremely
déséquilibrée en fait extrêmement
focused on the greens, on exports,
tourner vers les verts les exportations
I would have liked to react to the part
moi j'aurais aimé réagir sur la partie
and to the part Rollin obviously I completely
et sur la partie rollin videmment je
share the vision, in particular,
partage tout à fait la vision notamment
which is an aberration to bring
qui est une aberration d'aller faire
countries such as obviously
entrer des pays tels que évidemment
Cyprus, well even the address, into
chypre enfin même l'adresse dans une
a monetary zone like
dans une zone monétaire comme comme les
Europe, there is very little discussion on this
l'europe ait assez peu discussion là
and where there can be one is
dessus et là où il peut y en avoir une
even, can we make a
c'est même est ce qu'on peut faire une
single currency and enter between
monnaie unique est rentrer entre entre
countries, in any case, for it to work, what
les pays en tout cas pour que ça marche
are the conditions and do
quelles sont les conditions et est ce
these conditions exist in
que ces conditions sont existants en
Europe? I think it is impossible,
europe moi je pense qu'il est impossible
impossible, within a five-year timeframe, to
impossible un horizon de cinq ans temps
make a single currency between
d'aller faire une monnaie unique entre
France and Germany, for example,
la france et l'allemagne par exemple
why?  Obviously, when you
pourquoi parce qu'évidemment quand vous
create a single currency, you
faites une monnaie unique vous vous
deprive yourself of tears of hunger, inevitably
privez de larmes de la faim forcément
of valuation, or at least depreciations,
d'évaluation en tout cas dépréciations
to try to rebalance
pour tenter de rééquilibrer des
divergent economies. If you create a
économies divergentes si vous faites une
single currency, in case of
monnaie unique il va falloir en cas
competitiveness gaps,
d'écarts de compétitivité
things will have to be rebalanced, and if there are more
rééquilibrer les choses et s'il ya plus
possibilities to do something at the
de possibilités faire quelque chose au
level of currencies, it must be done at the
niveau des monnaies il faut les faire au
level of wages, of the
niveau où des salaires de la
competitiveness of countries. In any case, we
compétitivité des pays en tout cas il
need, firstly, to be countries
faut que 1 d'une part on est des pays
that are more or less capable of
qui soit capable plus ou moins de se
reforming themselves, and secondly, to have
réformer et deuxièmement d'avoir des
countries that have a vision no longer of
pays qui ait une vision non plus de
economic warfare but of
guerre économique mais de paix
economic peace, just as today
économique tout comme aujourd'hui
Alsace is not trying to lower its
l'alsace à n'essaye pas de baisser ses
wages compared to
salaires par rapport
Midi-Pyrénées; it cannot work,
midi pyrénées ça ne peut pas marcher
forced into this situation. So they need to have
contrainte dans cette situation là donc
a real vision of
il faut qu'ils aient une vraie vision de
cooperation. Today, the end of 15 years
coopération aujourd'hui fin 15 ans
of experience with the euro shows that we are, on the
d'expérience de l'euro montre qu'on est
contrary, in increasingly
au contraire dans des phases de plus en
divergent phases where each country does what it
plus divergentes où chaque pays fait ce
wants without asking the opinion of
qu'il veut sans demander l'avis aux
others.  Germany cut
autres quand l'allemagne baisse des
wages in 2002-2003, not asking the
salaires en 2002-2003 demande pas les
elderly to do the same. Ireland lowered its
vieux autres qu'en irlande baisse son
corporate tax rate for
taux d'impôt sur les sociétés des
banks, not for others. France
banques pas aux autres quoi la france
implemented the 35-hour workweek and didn't ask
fait les 35 heures elle ne demande pas
others to do the same, whether it was good or bad. In
aux autres bien ou mal peu importe en
any case, each country did what it
tout cas chaque pays a fait ce qu'il a
wanted without realizing that we
voulu son se dire que de toute façon on
are all sharing a
est en train de partager un espace
common space. What about the currency,
commun qui est qui et la monnaie
sir? What
monsieur de la marche qu'est ce que vous
can you tell me about Ireland and
pouvez me dire sur l'irlande sur le
Irish taxation? Ireland is an
fiscalité irlandaise l'irlande c'est une
aberration. Ireland was
aberration c'est à dire que l'irlande
a country with
c'était un pays sur lequel il y avait
three sheep and
trois moutons et de distilleries de
whiskey distilleries, okay, a pipe for poor countries, and
whisky d'accord pipe aux pays pauvres et
we brought it into the euro. So I completely
on le faire entrer dans l'euro alors je
agree with
suis tout à fait d'accord avec avec
Olivier. We bring them into the euro,
olivier on fait entrer dans l'euro
we authorize them or not, or we
on les autorise ou non les pouces où on
suggest it. I don't know exactly how
leur suggère je ne sais pas exactement
it happened, but secondly, to
comment ça s'est passé mais de deux de
create a quasi-free zone with a
faire une zone quasi franche avec un
tax on  12%, so in fact, we
impôt à 12% donc en fait on se sont
introduced ourselves into the euro, a tax haven. That's exactly what it is.
introduits dans l'euro un paradis fiscal
We don't
1 c'est ni plus ni moins ça on n'en
talk about it much as a
parle pas beaucoup comme un paradis
tax haven today; we focus more on
fiscal aujourd'hui on s'occupe plutôt de
Switzerland, but it is one. And
la suisse mais c'en est un et
in fact, it can't work. That is to
et de fait ça ne peut pas marcher c'est
say, we invest heavily there, but we
à dire qu'on s'y noculak engrais mais on
wait for it to blow over. And then, obviously, when
attend que ça se passe et après quand
it created a bubble—a
évidemment ça a créé une bulle une bulle
real estate bubble, a bubble
immobilière une bulle
in Ireland—and that bubble burst,
en irlande et que cette bulle a explosé
and we had to bail out the
et qu'il a fallu aller sauver les
banks, the Irish said, "Oh yeah,
banques les irlandais ont dit ah ouais
but if we break the
mais sion si on casse le modèle de
12% tax model, we're finished." So
d'impôt à 12% on est finie alors tout de
immediately, Europe went to hell in a handbasket. So we keep this
suite l'europe à dia bomba donc on garde
model. It's ridiculous; it can't
son garde ce modèle c'est ridicule ça ne
work. It can't
peut pas fonctionner ça ne peut pas
work. And this is the outline that
fonctionner et ça on l'a esquisse qui
is astonishing. Or even, you talked about
est étonnante ou même vous avez parlé du
the euro's structure, but that was much
montage de l'euro mais c'est bien plus
later. We brought them into
tard on a fait rentrer chez eux en 2008
the euro in 2008, so we know it doesn't
dans l'euro c'est donc on sait que ça
work.  We know there's a problem,
marche pas on sait qu'il ya un problème
but we keep going. Bernard wouldn't have let
mais on continue bernard encore n'aurait
Cyprus in either.
fait rentrer chypre
Nobody knows that, that's the
chaque personne ne le sait c'est ça le
tragedy. It's that no European, none of the
drame c'est qu'aucun européen aucun des
400 million Europeans, is aware of this. That's why we
400 millions d'européens de c'est pour
created this very chic currency. And besides,
qu'on a fait un très chic et d'ailleurs
none of the 400 million Europeans
aucun des 400 millions européen a suivi
closely followed the process of developing
de près le processus d'élaboration de
the euro and the fact that we put the
l'euro et le fait qu' on a mis la
cart before the horse. That is to say, we should have
charrue avant les boeufs c'est à dire
waited for greater
qu'il aurait fallu attendre une
convergence between
convergence accrue encore une fois entre
the economies of the states wishing to
les économies des états souhaitant
join this single currency before
entrer dans cette monnaie unique avant
creating it. We know that the United States
de la cré nous savons que les états unis
pushed the European Union to
ont poussé l'union européenne à
expand. We saw it with
s'élargir on l'a vu par rapport à la
Turkey, the negotiations on Turkey. Do
turquie les tractations sur la turquie
you think the
est-ce que vous pensez que les états
United States pushed Europe to expand
unis ont poussé l'europe à s'élargir
either to weaken it economically
soit pour l'affaiblir économiquement
to regain leadership, or was it
pour reprendre le leadership ou soit
pure and simple altruism?
c'était de l'altruisme pure et simple au
Initially, the Americans, and especially
départ les américains et surtout
Kissinger, when he was
kissinger d'ailleurs quand il était
Secretary of State, were involved.  The state's support for Nixon, in
secrétaire d'état auprès de nixon
particular, was effectively rejected during the
notamment repoussé effectivement à la
creation of Europe for a very
création de l'europe pour une raison
simple reason, and I
tout à fait simple et d'ailleurs je
believe it's important to respect it. He wanted to
crois qu'il faut respecter il souhaitait
definitively end the tensions that had arisen during the bloody
définitivement aux tensions qui a eu
conflicts that had plagued
lieu au conflit qui a eu lieu et qui
European countries in the past. They
européens dans le passé voilà ils
wanted to avoid a repetition
souhaitaient les éviter la répétition
of the conflicts that led to
des des conflits de la qui ont conduit à
the Second World War, and also to the
la seconde guerre mondiale et aussi à la
First, for that matter. And then, did
première d'ailleurs et a ensuite est-ce
they push
que l'extension ils ont poussé
massively for expansion? Yes, for reasons I don't know, to be
massivement oui alors pour des raisons
honest, to
que j'ignore à dire vrai ce que c'était
weaken Europe.
pour affaiblir l'europe
I think we shouldn't always accuse
je crois qu'il faut pas toujours accuser
states of Machiavellianism.
les états de machiavélisme l'état hélas
Unfortunately, sometimes, in Bouaké, the state is less
d'ailleurs parfois sur bouaké moins
Machiavellian. We imagine Olivier the Raja, or
machiavélique on imagine olivier le raja
why Cyprus? I
soit pourquoi pourquoi chypre moi je
simply think it was brought in
pense simplement qu'on l'a fait rentrer
unconsciously. So, just as we created
par inconscience donc comme on a fait
the euro unconsciously, when we dig
l'euro par inconscience quand on creuse
a little deeper, we see why we
un peu pourquoi on a fait l'euro on a
created the euro as a political symbol.
fait l'euro comme un symbole politique
European integration is a
d'intégration européenne semences un
nice symbol of political integration, its
joli symbole d'intégration politique ses
practices of having a single currency in
pratiques d'avoir une seule monnaie dans
the zone. The difficulty is that it has
la zone la difficulté que c'est que ça a
extremely heavy consequences on
qui sont extrêmement lourdes sur sur les
economies after 10 to 15 years. Besides, we would let them
économies d'ailleurs on les laisserait
do it, but no, it's very simple
faire mais non c'est très simple
today to go for a single currency
aujourd'hui d'aller fans monnaie unique
between Europe and China:
entre l'europe et la chine
1. We agree with the
1 on se met d'accord avec les dirigeants
Chinese leaders to create a central bank;
chinois de ont créé une banque centrale
3. It likes euros in the zone, it's
3 elle aimait d euros yann dans la zone
not complicated. However, after
c'est pas compliqué par contre au bout
ten years you will realize
de dix ans vous allez vous apercevoir
that while unemployment in Europe is at 25%, things are
que vaille à 25 % de chômage en europe
better in China. But that is to
est que ça va mieux en chine mais c'est
say, it takes a lot of time to
à dire il faut beaucoup de temps pour
see the negative consequences of a
voir les conséquences négatives d'une
very nice political decision. We
décision très sympathique politique on
continue, by the way, Latvia
continue d'ailleurs enfin la lettonie
with 10 withdrawals on January 1st or the 14th,
avec 10 retraits au 1er janvier ou le 14
it will be continuous, and that means
ça va faire en continu et c'est à dire
we have a problem. We know that the euro
que on a un problème on sait que l'euro
is still very, very sick
est quand même très très malade
today, even if afterwards we can
aujourd'hui même si après on peut
always say that  What will explode, what won't, it doesn't
toujours dire ce qui va éclater ce qui
matter. We have a
va pas éclater peu importe on a une
sick currency, a
monnaie qui est malade on a un système
sick system, a system in which
qui est malade on a un système dans
we're getting more and more indebted
lequel on s'endette de plus en plus pour
trying to bail out this or that country, and
essayer de venir au secours de un tel ou
today all we can think
d'un tel est aujourd'hui tout ce qu'on
to do is keep letting
trouve à faire c'est continuer à faire
countries into the Eurozone. It's against all common
rentrer des pays c'est en dépit de tout
sense to let countries into the
bon sens faire rentrer des pays dans le
Eurozone. They'll tell me, "Yes,
dans le la zone euro on va me dire oui
we committed to it," but whatever. We have a
on s'y était engagé peu importe on a un
problem today, and instead of trying
problème aujourd'hui au lieu d'essayer
to solve it, we're trying to make it
de le régler on est en train d'essayer
worse. So what I remember most is that what's
de l'aggraver donc je retiens surtout
crazy is that,
que ce qu'est ce qu'il ya c'est fou
for example, we haven't even been given a
c'est par exemple on ne m'a même pas
rule for joining the
comme règle pour entrer dans la zone
Eurozone to have, for instance, an
euro d'avoir par exemple un salaire
average salary at least equal to the
moyen au moins égale à la moyenne de la
Eurozone average or a corporate tax rate
zone euro ou un taux d'impôt sur les
at least equal to the average,
sociétés au moins égale à la moyenne
to stop dragging things down and
pour arrêter de tirer vers le bas et
increasing the divergences within the zone. One
d'augmenter les divergences de la zone
last point about Latvia, which is
dernier point sur la lettonie qu'on
already being called the future Cyprus, by the way.
appelle déjà la future chypre quand même
Because it's obviously a country with
parce que c'est évidemment un pays à
very low taxes, which is
très basses fiscalité pesant qui est
true, and 9% of Latvians are in favor of
vrai que 9% des lettons qui sont pour
joining the Eurozone, but still, it's
entrer dans la zone euro mais enfin
fantastic. Behind
c'est quand même fantastique derrière la
Latvia, four or five floors are being built,
lettonie quatre ou cinq étages sont en
no, but what an effect! We
train de café non mais quel effet
see a whole bunch of several
on voit tout un tas plusieurs états de
European states, the UCIA, Poland, but I
l'europe de l'uciac la pologne mais je
think they're showing wisdom. Yes,
crois qui fait preuve de sagesse oui
exactly. I'm coming back to the
exactement je reviens encore sur
deer and the bank deposit guarantee fund. Is it
chevreuil et le fonds de garantie des
properly provisioned? Have there been
correctement provisionnés est ce que il
exercises to be able to
ya eu des exercices pour pouvoir le
implement it quickly,
mettre en place rapidement des
simulations to put it in place? Do
simulations pour mettre en place est-ce
you think that the public authorities,
que vous pensez que les pouvoirs publics
at least the French ones, are able to
au moins un français sont en mesure de
guarantee to the French that if a state
garantir aux français qu'eux si un état
or their
ou si leur ont fait défaut ou si leur
bank defaults, their
banque fait défaut est-ce que leur
euro savings will be guaranteed up to
épargne en euros sera garantie à hauteur
100 million?
de 100 millions
The guarantee fund isn't very
pour le fonds de garantie est quand même
big, it only has
pas bien pas bien gros il n'a que des
billions of euros currently. What does "
milliards actuellement d'euros qu'est ce
not very big" mean?
que ça veut dire pas bien gros
By admin, billions more or less of deposits, and
by admin milliards à peu près de dépôts
the fund is 2  Billions, that being said,
est le fonds fait 2 milliards ceci étant
you still have a buffer
vous avez malgré tout un amortisseur qui
concerning uninsured deposits,
concerne les dépôts non garantis en ci
representing roughly 500 billion in
représente à peu près 500 milliards sur
total. So, in other words, even if there aren't
l'ensemble donc autrement dit en cas pas
500 billion in losses and only two of the
à 500 milliards de pertes a que deux des
major depositors haven't left the
gros déposants ont pas quitté le système
banking system, you can still absorb a great many
bancaire vous pouvez amortir tout de
shocks.
même beaucoup beaucoup beaucoup de chocs
What's more troubling, by the way, is the
ce qui est plus gênant d'ailleurs sur le
deposit guarantee fund. We've
fonds de garantie des dépôts on a très
barely mentioned it in the current banking law; it's being
peu parlé dans la loi bancaire actuel il
merged with a
est en train d'être fusionnée avec un
guarantee fund, or rather a
fonds de garantie enfin un fonds de
resolution fund, which is supposed to help
résolution qui doit venir en aide aux
banks in difficulty.
banques en difficulté
In other words, we're
autrement dit on est en train de
mixing funds that were meant
mélanger les fonds qui étaient censés
solely to
être destiné uniquement à la
protect depositors' savings
préservation de l'épargné des déposants
with a fund that could be used to
vers un fonds qui pourra servir à
recapitalize Crédit Agricole or
recapitaliser demain crédit agricole ou
Société Générale tomorrow, whereas it would have been
société générale alors qu'ils ont été
much healthier to create two
beaucoup plus sain de faire deux fonds
separate funds, as Europe allowed.
différents comme l'europe le permettait
Speaking of funds, Mr. de la
en parlant des fonds monsieur de la
Marche, what do you think of
marche qu'est ce que vous pensez des
the European Central Bank's equity? The
fonds propres de la banque centrale
European Central Bank's equity... I don't know, it's
européenne je sais pas c'est pas c'est
not a problem since
pas un problème puisque
nothing has nothing  Nevertheless, we've
puisque rien n'a rien n'empêche on l'a
seen it many times, so nothing
vu quand même de nombreux soit rien
prevents printing money.
n'empêche de faire marcher la planche à
Therefore, from that point on, the
billets donc à partir de ce moment là le
balance sheets of central banks and their equity
bilan des banques centrales et le le le
capital aren't particularly important. That's the
les fonds propres des banques centrales
only thing
intérêt fou là c'est la seule chose
we can say. Today,
qu'on peut dire c'est qu'aujourd'hui
you saw what happened with the so-
vous avez vous avez vu ce qui s'est
called
passé au moment de du soi-disant
EC2 regulation of Greece, the haircut. What happened?
ce2 de la grèce le haircut qui c'est qui
Why did we create
s'est passé pourquoi est ce qu'on a fait
an air code that was, in fact, quite limited—
un air code qui était en en fait tout à
I remind you, limited—
fait limité est limité je vous rappelle
to the obliques that were under Greek law, and
aux obliques qui était de droit grec et
not to the obliques under
non pas aux obliques de droit
international law that obligate the hobbies of
international qui obligent les hobbies
Greek law bonds, that is to
des obligations de de droit grec c'est à
say, issued under Greek law, so basically
dire émis en droit greg donc en gros
held only by
détenu uniquement par les banques
Greek banks? Everything
grecques tout ce qui était
issued under international law was not
émis en droit international n'était pas
affected by the haircut. But above all,
concertés concernés par le hair cut mais
the ECB said yes, I'm fine with it
c'est surtout que la bce a dit oui je
for the private sector, but not
veux bien pour le secteur privé mais pas
for me, because between what they
pour moi parce que entre ce qu'ils
had directly in the...
avaient en direct dans les obligations
Greek sovereign bonds plus the
souveraines grecques plus les
collateral they had accepted, it
collatéraux qu'ils avaient accepté il
amounted to 200 billion.
avait il en allait pour 200 milliards
Okay, so 100 billion, 75% makes
bon alors de 100 milliards 75% ça fait
150. The ECB's equity, if I
150 les fonds propres de la bce de
remember correctly, should be around 13
mémoires doivent être autour de 13
billion, I think.
milliards il me semble se confirmer
13 billion - 150, that's
13 milliards 13 milliards - 150 ça fait
still a big hole and it's
quand même un gros trou et ça fait
messy,
désordre
so there you go. But today,
donc voila mais aujourd'hui
otherwise
sinon
we're also talking about this on the
on parle de ça aussi sur le sur le bilan
Fed's balance sheet. No matter the Fed's balance sheet, it
de la fed peu importe le bilan de la fed
can, it could, at the limit,
il peut il pourrait à la limite
almost double. You just have to print what's
quasiment doublé il suffit d'imprimer ce
needed. Mr. Bernanke isn't
qu'il faut monsieur bernanke n'est pas
a great specialist in this. They've given us
un grand spécialiste de ça ils nous ont
4 billion every day.
fait 4 milliards tous les jours
If needed, they'll give us 8. I've
s'il ya besoin il en fera 8 me suis
committed. I see you smiling. No, no, I
engagé je vous vois sourire non non je
am
suis
indeed  Fortunately,
effectivement heureusement d'ailleurs
what keeps things running is, in a
qui fait tourner il est d'une certaine
way, the American printing press,
façon la planche à billets américaine
because it injects liquidity
parce qu'il introduit des liquidités
into the system, and that allows
dans le dispositif et ça permet de
interest rates to remain low.
maintenir des taux d'intérêt faibles
All of this is part of the lottery, his own, during
enfin tout ça dans la loterie siens dans
the crisis, but not in the
la crise mais pas dans l'économie
clumsy economy. In economics, the
maladroite en économie berroyer les
funds, the funds issued by the
fonds les fonds émis par la banque
American central bank, the Fed, still are
centrale américaine la fed n'arrive
n't reaching the real economy.
toujours pas sur l'économie réelle
Why is a pope, at what it's worth
pourquoi un pape à ce que vaut
today, staying in the
aujourd'hui reste dans la partie
financial economy? Well, it's getting there
d'économie financière enfin ça y arrive
because it's one of the six directly,
parce que c'est un des six directement
but it's true that it serves to fuel
mais c'est vrai que ça sert à alimenter
speculative futures for the most part, and
déçu spéculatifs pour la plupart et
it's not for nothing that
c'est pas pour rien qu'il est tout de
the American stock market is still hungry and returning to its
même la bourse américaine et retrouve
pre-crisis levels.
ses niveaux d'avant la crise a faim
It's still so realistic,
c'est quand même si réaliste
you really think these funds are
vous pensez vraiment que ces fonds sont
there to maintain the various
là pour maintenir les différents indices
stock market indices, Hassan Haddad? But it's in
boursiers hassan hadad mais il est en
decline, we told you, he said it
berne on te l'a dit il l'a dit
officially, he said
officiellement il a dit
it only serves one purpose: to make it
ça ne sert qu'à une chose c'est à faire
rise on Monday. So it's good, there isn't, there isn't  There are no
monter lundi ce donc c'est bien pas il
other reasons.
n'ya pas il n'y a pas d'autres raisons
I don't know if you remember, but back
je sais pas si vous vous souvenez vous
in 2011, the Bank
en 2011 quand même la banque
of England asked a
d'angleterre a demandé un rapport à un
number of experts for a report, asking what the
certain nombre d'experts en demandant ce
consequences were, what
qu'ils quelles étaient les conséquences
portion
qu'elle était là qu'elle était la partie
of its quantitative easing had
de son quantitative easing qui était
returned to the economy. If you
revenu dans l'économie pas si vous vous
remember what happened, after a
souvenez de ce qui s'est passé au bout
while, the experts came back to
d'un moment les experts reviennent
the Bank of England, gave
auprès de la banque d'angleterre donnent
their report, saying that barely 3%
leur rapport en disant il ya à peine 3 %
of the quantitative easing had entered
du quantitative easing qui est rentré
the real economy. The Bank of England's
dans l'économie réelle
conclusion was simple: let's do a
conclusion de la bo bas on en refait un
second round. It worked so well, and it's a good thing
deuxième ça a si bien marché et encore
it didn't return to
heureux que ça ne revienne pas dans
the economy, because given the massive amounts
l'économie puisque vu les masses qui
injected, its share would make my
sont injectés sa part ferait pleurer ma
inflation level, which is still
niveau d'inflation tout de même non
significant, suffer. A major bond bubble in the
négligeable acquis dans le système
current system of low interest rates
actuel de taux bas de bulle obligataire
would be catastrophic for
majeur serait catastrophique pour
the accounts of the banks and
voilà pour les comptes des banques et
their cronies. Simon, a
des détenteurs de ses affidés simon un
quick word on
petit mot sur la politique de
Japan's quantitative easing policy: what do
quantitative easing du japon qu'est ce
you think, sir? Exemplary
que vous en pensez monsieur exemplaire
policy...
de la politique la politique de
Quantitative easing is following
quantitative easing c'est suivre suivre
the policy to print or
la politique pour imprimer ou faire
devalue its currency. Well, I didn't have any
dévaluer sa monnaie bon là je n'avais
idea. The Japanese show is so
pas d'idée show le japonais tellement en
current on Japan, he just committed
cours sur le japon il vient de se
suicide. What? Why is he arousing
suicider quoi pourquoi il suscite de
more and more interest? I drank, I saw a
plus en plus j'ai bu j'ai vu un
statement from
déclaration de de
Mr. AB this weekend, or to immunize
monsieur ab ce week-end ou d'immuniser
finances, it doesn't matter
finances peu importe
who announces it, it's a kind of one-upmanship. It's like
qui annonce est une espèce de surenchère
two teenagers in the
on dirait deux adolescents dans la cour
schoolyard. A series of measures is the one
d'école un train de mesures est celui
who goes the furthest. Sika Health
qui va le plus loin sika health
Interview knows the former
interview connaît l'ancien ministre des
Japanese finance minister. If you had to
finances japonais si vous devriez si
ask him a question,
vous deviez lui poser une question
what questions would you ask him?
quelles questions vous lui poserez
Bees are judging each other, how far they will go
abeilles se jugent jusqu'où ils vont
in the south, that is to say, there they seem to be
aller dans le sud c'est à dire là ils
accelerating
ont l'air d'accélérer quand même pas mal
things quite a bit, I tell you, they are in the process of
les choses je vous dis sont en train de
being in competition with Mr.
2,2 d'être en compet avec monsieur
Bernanke, it's about who buys back
bernanke c'est à celui qui rachète fera
the most bonds.
le plus d'obligations
They announced figures that
mène là ils ont annoncé des chiffres qui
are totally astounding, so
sont totalement ahurissant donc
you're going to have, I think everyone is
vous allez avoir je pense que le tout le
bloody today because
monde de blood aujourd'hui pour parce
the  The yen had gone from 81.13 on
que le yen était passé de 81 13 sur
this good news to 98. I think we haven't seen the last of it
cette bonne nouvelle à 98 je pense qu'on
falling, and that it
n'a pas fini de le voir baisser et que
really is, for once,
c'est vraiment pour le coup c'est
a monkey's currency. That is to
vraiment une monnaie de singe c'est à
say,
dire que il faut qu il faut qu faudrait
central bankers really need to
quand même que les banquiers centraux
stop thinking that by playing
arrête de penser que en jouant au
Monopoly they can fix an
monopoly on arrive à redresser une
economy. They're in the middle of a game of Monopoly, in a full-blown cash grab, a full-blown
économie là il son lit sont en plein jeu
cavalcade, and it's going to end
pleine cavalerie et ça va se terminer
very badly, sir.
très mal monsieur monsieur
It's a completely
annoncé c'est un phénomène tout à fait
mysterious phenomenon, I mean, created at the beginning of
mystérieux je veux dire créé au début de
the pause that was initially called the "
la pause qu'on appelait au départ la
Japan pause." I played it; I felt that it was certainly...
pose du japon j'ai joué je sentais qu'il
I don't think it's
s'agit certainement comme je ne pense
mysterious, for a monkey
pas que ce soit mystérieux pour singer
view, it's a competitive devaluation
view c'est une dévaluation compétitive
between... I'm going to take three major
entre entre je vais prendre trois grands
blocs: Japan, Europe, and the
blocs le japon l'europe et les états
United States, and I'll get you to jump on that. On
unis et je vous ferai rebondir dessus
the subject of economic warfare, Mr.
sur le sujet guerre économique monsieur
Bérurier, the message to say is indeed, it was
bérurier message à dire en effet la
an act of
bouche c'était un acte de guerre
economic warfare through devaluation, but it
économique par par d'évaluation mais ça
goes much further than that since  It's
va beaucoup plus loin que ça puisque
really about triggering
c'est vraiment vouloir déclencher de de
inflation to a certain level, and it's a real pain.
l'inflation un niveau et c'est carabine
Given the levels that are being
et vu les niveaux qui sont qui sont
printed, and I'm going back to what I was
imprimés et je reviens sur ce que je
saying earlier, when you have
disais tout à l'heure quand vous avez
two to three times more debt than
deux à trois fois plus de dette que ce
you'll ever be able to repay, your
que vous pourrez jamais rembourser votre
situation is quite desperate. So
situation qui est assez désespérée donc
you continue your gamble as long as
vous continuez votre cavalerie tant que
it works, and how do you get out of it? Either
ça marche et vous en sortez comment soit
you really try to raise those
vous tentez vraiment de lever ces
sums in the form of taxes, and that
sommes-là sous forme d'impôts et la
part triggers a recession, which
partie déclenché la récession carabine
will increase anyway, along with
et qui de toute façon vont augmenter
deficits; or you default like the
elle même et déficits soit vous faites
Greeks, saying, "Oh
un défaut francs à la grecque en disant
no, excuse me, I really can't
ah non excusez moi vraiment je peux pas
repay, let's renegotiate and see what
remboursé renégocions et puis voyons la
loss you'll take"; or
perte que que vous allez prendre soit
you actually try to play with
vous tentez effectivement de jouer avec
your central bank to repay in worthless
votre banque centrale pour rembourser en
currency by using the
monnaie de singe en utilisant la planche
printing press, but that's a form
à billets mais ce qui est une forme
of aid. There also needs to be
d'aidé faut également qu'il est
inflation for Hamburg, yes,
l'inflation pour hambourg ce oui
obviously, that's what
évidemment
I think will happen
c'est je pense à ce qui va se passer en
first where it's possible. Don't
premier lieu là où ce sera possible
ask too much in Europe, but in the
demandez pas trop en europe mais aux
United States, in Japan, it's...  It's quite logical
états-unis au japon c'est assez logique
that this is happening because why is it
qui se passe ça parce que pourquoi ces
easier, in quotes, even
c'est plus facile entre guillemets même
if it's more instructors for
si c'est plus d'instructeurs pour
the economy, it's undoubtedly the most
l'économie est sans doute le plus
unjust,
injuste
managed by political cowardice, it's better to
géré par lâcheté politique vaut mieux
start with that, it's
commencer par ça c'est une lâcheté
political cowardice, obviously
politique évidemment une lâcheté
political cowardice is an art, not daring to
politique est un art ne pas oser allait
renegotiate his debt and say it, but I'll
renégocier sa dette et le dire mais je
repay you by printing
vous rembourser en imprimant des sommes
colossal sums and Saturday after, there's a real
colossales et samedi derrière ya un vrai
problem, changed, so I didn't come, the
problème changé donc je ne venais pas la
solution for me, that this country has
solution pour me paquet que ce pays a
experienced an absolutely frenzied ride
connu une chevauchée absolument effrénée
for the economy, that starting from
sur pour l'économie qu'un partant de
very low, one day the
très bas arrivera un jour le niveau de
Western standard of living in Dr. Raucourt and
vie occidental dans dr raucourt et
relaxation, annual growth of the order of
détente croissance annuelle de l'ordre
7 to 10%, and then suddenly everything
de 7 à 10% et puis tout à coup tout
stopped, and it's been a good fifteen years since
s'est arrêté et ça fait bien quinze ans
this stop, during which the blues have made people say it's the
que cet arrêt durant des bleus ont fait
warrior's rest, in a way, the
se dire c'est le repos du guerrier d'une
Japanese, a pause
certaine façon des japonais une pause
in growth, and not at all, it's
dans la croissance et pas du tout c'est
a complete stop, they haven't, they can't get out,
un arrêt complet qui ne l'ont ils
and they have
n'arrivent pas à sortir et ils ont
experienced, I don't  I know how many
expérimenté je ne sais combien de
prime ministers have had economic policies,
premier ministre de politique économique
and it still doesn't seem as if, in a
et inand semble toujours pas comme si
way, the Japanese
d'une certaine façon les japonais
were made to climb
étaient faits pour gravir des montagnes
very steep mountains, but not at all
très pentu très raide mais pas du tout
to manage a plateau. Don't you
pour gérer un plateau est ce que vous ne
think we're facing two
pensez pas qu'on est face à deux à deux
phenomena, and Japan is somewhat
phénomènes et le japon et quelque part
ahead of us, showing the way,
un peu en avance sur nous montre la voie
which is that, firstly,
qui est que 1 d'une part un bas
the economy was developing, and it's
l'économie allait développer la haye et
beautiful, there's pretty much everything
c'est beau il ya à peu près tout ce
needed on average for the
qu'il faut en moyenne en moyenne pour la
population. It's difficult to make
population c'est difficile d'aller me
an economy grow that has already
faire croître une économie qui a déjà
grown. And secondly, it's an aging economy, it's
crû et deuxièmement c'est une économie
an aging population, it
c'est une population vieillissante elle
's decreasing.
est en train de diminuer la population
So, besides the decline in the
du japon donc outre la dives la baisse
number of people and especially the
du nombre de personnes et surtout le
aging population, it's a
vieillissement donc c'était économie
much less dynamic economy than in the
beaucoup moins dynamique que par le
past, and therefore reaching a kind of
passé et donc arriver une forme de
growth plateau is
plateaux de croissance c'est
relatively logical, and I think that's what's in
relativement logique et je pense que
front of us. The question
c'est ce qui est devant nous la question
is, why don't we think about what we
est pourquoi ne réfléchissons pas sûr
do when we're in
qu'est ce qu'on fait quand je suis dans
a zero-growth regime? We see  That
un régime de croissance nulle on voit
today there is an
qu'aujourd'hui il ya un refus
almost fundamentalist refusal, have you considered
quasi intégristes les avez-vous pensé à
that it's not a refusal but rather
que ce n'est pas un refus mais plutôt
a group formed with a style
un groupe ayant été formé avec un style
of thinking? And like them, they
de pensée et comme ceux ci de penser ils
will continue to think, or at least
vont continuer à faire du moins à
try to perpetuate this system of
essayer de faire perdurer ce système de
thought. They haven't learned to think
pensée ils n'ont pas appris à penser en
outside the box. But that's what
dehors de la boîte ça mais c'est ce que
I call a denial of reality. I mean, I'm
j'appelle un déni de réalité
37 years old. Growth went off to
enfin moi j'ai 37 ans la croissance elle
buy cigarettes before
est parti acheter des clopes avant que
I was even born. It arrived, and we
je naisse quoi elle est parvenue et on
keep saying "next year" and "it
continue à dire l'année prochaine et
will be here." We're going to have to say it won't
sera là il va falloir qu'on dit elle
come back to us and adopt
nous reviendra plus et qu'on adopte
the economic model. It's dramatic. It's stupid. Not
l'économie est dramatique c'est con non
only are we obviously doing nothing,
seulement évidemment on ne fait rien
but we're not even there yet. Well, we
mais on n'en est même pas là bien on
refuse to think about it. There's practically
refuse de le penser il a pratiquement
no economist in France who
pas un économiste en france qui
thinks about what to do with
réfléchis qu'est ce que je fais en
zero growth. You can't find a
croissance nulle vous ne trouvez pas une
thesis, you can't find funding
thèse vous trouvez pas des financements
to reflect on this obsession, not an
pour réfléchir sur sa manie ni un
economist or a politician. Look at the
économiste et un politique regardez les
statements of the Minister of Finance,
déclarations de ministre des finances
Mr. Moscovici, who says
monsieur moscovici qui lui dit
yes to it.  It doesn't mean anything else, so
oui alors veut pas dire autrement donc
whoever says we'll have zero growth in 2013
qui dit on aura zéro croissance en 2013
and puts 1.3% in 2014 and 2% in 2015, that's it, we're back to square one
et met 1 3 en 2014 2 en 2015 ça y est on
like in 2014, so that's what it will be like.
est reparti comme en 14 donc ça sera ça
You'll see that at the beginning of 2014, he'll say, "Oh well,
vous verrez que début 2014 il dira ah
yes, I have to admit that we're
bah oui je dois convenir que nous sommes
still at zero, even negative," and "
toujours à zéro voire en négatif et
But don't worry, in 2015 we'll
mais vous inquiétez pas en 2015 on
pick up again, and in 2016 we'll have 3%
reprend et en 2016 on aura 3 % de
growth." It's always the same thing, it's been going on for
croissance c'est toujours la même chose
twenty years, as
ça fait vingt ans que ça dure comme
Olivier says. So, because we haven't
comme le dit olivier donc parce qu'on
realized that, in fact, while for years the 2014
s'est pas aperçu que en fait alors
curve hasn't reversed, which was constructed by some
courbe de 2 2 qui a été construite par
American economist, I don't remember which one,
je sais plus quel économiste américain
who said that since 1950 we've lost one
qui dit qu depuis 1950 on perd un
percent of our population every ten years, we've lost one percent of our
pourcent de conscience tous les dix ans
growth every ten
on perd 1% de croissance tous les dix
years, so we'll have to get used to it.
ans donc il va falloir s'y faire
Today we're no longer in a
aujourd'hui on est plus dans une dans un
system where we had growth through
système où on avait de la croissance par
demographics; that's over in
la démographie là c'est fini dans
many countries.  It's not just over in
beaucoup de pays c'est pas fini qu'au
Japan, it's over in Germany, it's over in the
japon c'est finir en allemagne c'est
United States, it's over in China
fini aux états unis s'est finie en chine
with their one-child policy, it's over in
avec leur politique de l'enfant unique
a large part
c'est fini dans dans une grande partie
of the world, and you have, in addition to
du monde et vous avez en plus
helping, everything related to
d'aider tout ce qui est
industrialization, internal combustion engines,
industrialisation moteur à explosion
electricity, etc., which doesn't
électricité etc qui ne qui ne se
reproduce today. So
reproduise pas aujourd'hui donc
today, it's not because your
aujourd'hui c'est pas parce que votre
iPad is going to be twice as fast that it's going to
ipad va aller deux fois plus vite que ça
change the world and bring
va changer le monde donc et que ça va
you growth and
vous apporter de la croissance et la
productivity. So the only productivity
productivité donc la seule productivité
we know today is
qu'on connaisse aujourd'hui c'est de
firing people, and that generally leads to
virer les gens et ça ça va en général il
a small return on investment, on the topline,
ya un petit retour sur le sur la topline
on the revenue, which happens
sur le sur le chiffre d'affaires qui se
quite quickly. I would like
fait assez rapidement jeu je voudrais
your opinion on this. There's a formula
votre regard dont il ya une formule
that could be applied in Japan by
qu'on pourrait impliquer au japon par
Einstein, which applies to the
nou ké d'einstein qui s'applique à l'
Aquila, itself applied to
aquila appliquer lui-même à la physique
fundamental physics, and which is the following:
fondamentale et qui est la suivante
think outside the box. Well, I wonder if
pensez à côté eh bien je me demande si
this formula wouldn't deserve to be
cette formule ne mériterait pas d'être
applied to  The economy,
appliqué à l'économie à l'économie du
especially Japan's, is rebounding. That's a
japon en particulier rebondir elle est
very good phrase too. Who said that we don't
très belle phrase aussi qui a dit qu'on
solve problems with the
ne résout pas les problèmes avec les
same thinking that created them? That's
mêmes modes de pensée qui les ont créés
exactly it. It's a
c'est exactement ça c'est une pensée
common thought. Also, Jacques Blanc,
commune aussi à jacques blanc
I'm going to ask you a question about the
je vais vous poser une question sur les
main macroeconomic players.
principaux acteurs macroéconomique
Have indicators been
l'indicateur indicateurs ont-ils été
misused, or is it a deficiency
dévoyé où c'est une carence des
in the interpretations of journalists and politicians? Do
journalistes et politiques dans leurs
you think
interprétations est-ce que vous pensez
these indicators are still effective
que ces indicateurs sont encore opérant
for a correct reading? What
pour une lecture correcte qu'est ce que
can you tell me about that?
vous pouvez me dire là dessus
UFR hardly talked about
ufr n'a quasiment pas parlé des
indicators and practically only mentioned one
indicateurs et n'a pratiquement qu'un
called growth.
qui s'appelle croissance croissance
Internal growth, and
croissance croissance interne et
growth, talking about an increase in the
croissance en parle d'augmentation du
gross domestic product, isn't uninteresting,
produit intérieur brut pas inintéressant
but the problem is that this
mais le problème c'est que un c'est
single indicator is extremely perfect. It's basically
extrêmement un parfait ce seul
the equivalent of
indicateur là c'est en gros l'équivalent
revenue for
d'un chiffre d'affaires pour les
companies. Imagine analyzing
entreprises imaginer que l'on analyse
companies just by looking at their
les entreprises juste en regardant leur
revenue and saying, "I hope the
chiffre d'affaires et que disait
revenue goes up soon."
vivement que le chiffre d'affaires monté
You never look at whether the result is
vous regardez jamais si le résultat est
positive or negative, but what if the  The
positif ou négatif mais et si le
result is negative, the lines between revenue and GDP are opaque.
résultat est négatif sont opaques entre
You
produit intérieur brut vous ne
never account for the fact that
comptabiliser dedans jamais le fait que
you're depleting natural resources like
vous tapez dans des ressources
oil, and you don't account for the
pétrole et vous ne comptabiliser pas la
pollution you generate. You
pollution que vous générez qu'il ya vous
talk about oil, but did you
parler du pétrole est ce que me
know about the peak of UBS and the rapid pace of
connaissait le pic de l'ubs et rapide de
oil production? Do you
production pétrolière et est-ce que vous
think the debts issued by these
pensez que les dettes émises ces
Ponzi schemes, these
pyramides de ponzi
state-sponsored ones, are a way to escape
celle étatiques sont une façon de fuir
the geological reality of energy?
la réalité géologique de l'énergie
Yes, so Alpiq deliberates at 17.67 yen.
oui alors alpiq délibère à 17 67 yens
It's a mathematical function that says
c'est une fonction mathématique qui dit
that from the moment you have a
qu'à partir du moment où vous avez un
finite stock of something and you use it,
stock de quelque chose fini et que vous
when you have
taper dedans quand vous avoir à la
production, it will rise, and then one day
production qui va monter puis un jour
it will reach zero
enfin ça va monter ça va arriver à zéro
when you're finished. So it goes through
quand vous aurez fini donc ça passe par
a maximum
un maximum
and then it falls again. And Hubert
et puis et puis ça redescend et hubert a
showed that on oil fields,
montré que sur des champs de pétrole en
it actually makes a nice, somewhat bell-shaped curve,
fait ça fait une jolie courbe un peu un
relatively symmetrical.
peu en cloche relativement symétrique
So far, no, we haven't reached the
jusqu'à présent non n'est pas arrivé au
global peak, which could  Changing
pic mondial qui pourrait changer changer
things doesn't necessarily have a peak; there will probably be
des choses n'en a pas forcément un pic
a plateau that will
en aura sans doute un plateau qui va
last, probably about ten years.
durer et sans doute une dizaine d'années
It's a peak that moves, yes, well, an
c'est une pique qui se déplace oui enfin
Olympic peak that moves a little,
olympique qui se déplace un petit peu
but anyway, we see your
mais enfin on voit de toute façon votre
plateau will last roughly between
plateau il va durer à peu près entre
2010 and 2020. That's roughly what we have. This
2010 et 2020 voilà à peu près ce qu'on
gentleman, I'm in D1. You were
ce monsieur je me suis en d1 vous étiez
close to the powers that be when the
proche des pouvoirs
first oil shock arrived.
à l'arrivée du premier choc pétrolier
How did the
comment se sont comportés les
French institutions behave to manage this
institutions françaises pour gérer c'est
new phenomenon?
ce phénomène nouveau
The first oil shock took place in
le premier choc pétrolier ait lieu à
the autumn of 1973. It was very
l'automne 1973 il s'est traduit été très
brutal. It resulted, in the event
brutal il s'est traduit dans la commune
published today, in a decline in the
publiée aujourd'hui par une décroissance
world's GDP. At the end of
de la du pnb mondial en fin de la
1974, most major developed countries saw a
plupart des grands pays développés en 74
2% drop. Recognizing what we
on a chuté de 2% des reconnu ce qu'on
had experienced, what we have experienced recently,
avait connu ce qu'on a connu récemment
I would say, then growth resumed. What we
je dirais puis la croissance a repris
have experienced, what we are very, very
ce qu'on a connu ce qu'on est très très
weak. How did what we have, like those we
faible comment ce qu'on a comme ceux
have known, or what we are  In
qu'on a connus ou ce que nous sommes en
short, we are getting to know
somme nous sommes en train de connaître
your background. There is a certain
vos derrière il ya un certain
parallelism regarding the
parallélisme en ce qui concerne la la
fall in GDP between the first
chute du pnb entre la première crise
oil crisis, and also the second one, that
pétrolière d'ailleurs aussi la seconde
of 2019-2010. Unfortunately, the
celle de 2 119 80 hélas la situation
current situation has nothing to do with the oil crisis,
actuelle les couve n'ont rien à voir
but in terms of economic situations, they
mais en tant de situations là économique
are extremely different.
s'en sont extrêmement différents
How did we manage this? First, we managed it proactively.
comment a t'on gérer ça m'a d'abord on a
That is to say, in a
géré par anticipation c'est à dire que
certain way, in France,
d'une certaine façon en france
we saw it coming, we had seen it coming,
on l'a vu venir on l'avait vu venir
since we
puisqu'on a
tried to protect ourselves against this
essayer de se prémunir contre cette
rise in oil prices by launching a
hausse du prix du pétrole en lançant un
large-scale nuclear program. It is quite
à grande échelle est tout à fait
implausible if they wanted to... if you
invraisemblable s'ils voulaient si vous
look at it with...
voulez quand vous le regardez avec le le
how to say... look at it today...
comment dire le regarde aujourd'hui les
today, in a few
une aide aujourd'hui on a en quelques
years, we have built, launched 30
années construit lancé 30 centrales
nuclear power plants. We have done something
nucléaires ont fait quelque chose
extravagant, something we will never do again. Was this
d'extravagant quelque chose qu'on ne
thought out before launching these thirty
réfléchi avant de lancer ses trente
centers? So yes, absolutely, it was carefully considered.
centres alors oui tout à fait ça a été
The occasion will require several
mûrement réfléchi à l'occasion plusieurs
advisors to remain at the Élysée Palace, which was
conseillers restera à l'elysée qui a
presided over by the Head of State, Georges
présidé le le chef de l'état georges
Pompidou. In this instance, I have to
pompidou en l'occurrence que j'ai à vous
prepare a report for you, and I have drafted
préparer d'ailleurs et dont j'ai rédigé
summaries of the decision, which had been
des relevés décision qui avait été
corrected by the Head of State. All
corrigé par le le chef de l'état tous
these summaries are from this restricted council meeting
ces relevés des sous c'est conseil
between Lyon and 69. They anticipated
restreint entre lyon 69 ont prévu
the possibility of a future rise in the price of
l'hypothèse un jour d'une hausse du prix
oil and the excessive dependence
du pétrole et la dépendance excessive
we had on oil for
que nous avions par rapport à ce pétrole
our energy supply,
dans notre approvisionnement énergétique
and this is what led to the launch of the
et c'est ce qui a conduit à ce lancement
massive Duclair Plan, on which
d'un plan duclair massif sur laquelle
we still live to a
nous vivons encore aujourd'hui dans dans
large extent today. How did
une large mesure comment se sont
other countries behave? Did
comportés les autres pays est ce que
you have any perception of the
vous avez eu une perception des services
intelligence services, for example, the German or
de renseignement par exemple allemand ou
Spanish? Were these
espagnol est ce que ces services de
intelligence services interested in your
renseignement se sont intéressés à vos
work, or were you alone
travaux ou est ce que vous étiez seul
against us? It wasn't
contre nous il s'agissait pas
specifically about the education services;
spécialement des services d enseignement
our work was public. I reported on
nos travaux étaient public a rendez
each restricted council meeting to the
compte de chaque conseil restreint au
journalist accredited to the Élysée Palace as soon as the
journaliste accrédité à l'elysée dès la
restricted council meeting ended.
fin de ce conseil restreint il suffisait
to observe our decisions and our
d'observer nos décisions et nos
decisions were
décisions étaient d'une grande clarté
indeed very clear, they have been imitated in
effectivement elles ont été imités dans
several countries, but the Americans
plusieurs pays mais les américaines
did not wait for the call,
n'avaient pas attendu appel est
a nuclear program was also launched
également lancé un programme nucléaire
before us, okay, but not on the same
avant nous d'accord mais pas de la même
scale in the building sector, so countries focused on
ampleur sur le bâtiment alors pays sur
oil, sir. I'm going to
le pétrole monsieur de la marche 1 je
ask you a question, I'll
vais vous poser une question je vais
try to be very simple:
essayer très simple
all these debts issued in our eyes
toutes ces dettes émises à nos yeux ne
are not based on any energy or
sont basées sur aucune réalité
calorific reality, that is to say, 1
énergétique calorifique c'est à dire 1
dollar, 1 euro is worth the same number of calories.
dollar 1 euro vaut autant de calories
We summarize purchasing power by
nous synthétisons le pouvoir d'achat par
the number of calories bought or
le nombre de calories acheter ou
assimilated. Do you think that
assimilables est-ce que vous pensez que
central banks are aware
les banques centrales sont conscientes
that currencies and money are not based
que les monnaies et nice ne sont basées
on any energy reality? Well,
sur aucune réalité énergétique
knowing what
près savoir de quoi est conscient
Mr. Bernanke or anyone else is aware of is
monsieur bernanke ou autre c'est
complicated,
compliqué
but
mais
whoever they are aware of, that in any
quelle qu'elle soit consciente que de
case the currency they issue is
toute façon le la monnaie qu'elle émette
based on nothing, I think they
mais basé sur rien je pense que oui
know that today. It's exactly
le savent aujourd'hui c'est exactement
as if to explain to people a little what it is
comme si pour expliquer aux gens un peu
because we talk a lot about
ce que c'est parce que le on parle
quantitative easing, printing money,
beaucoup de quantitative easing
etc., in
démission de planche à billets etc
general, and people  They don't understand much of what's being said,
général et les gens comprennent pas
but
mais
it's exactly as if today
c'est exactement aujourd'hui comme si
you had someone who liked 4
vous aviez quelqu'un qui aimait t 4
billion bad checks a day,
milliards par jour de chèques en bois
that is to say, checks based on nothing. If you're
c'est à dire basé sur rien si vous êtes
sure that the guy writing you a check
sûr que le type qui vous fait un chèque
in front of you has the funds in his
en face de vous à la provision sur son
account, it's worth something. You can
compte ça vaut quelque chose vous pouvez
go and exchange your check for
aller échanger votre chèque contre
something, for a car, for anything.
contre quelque chose contre une voiture
From the moment
contre n'importe quoi à partir du moment
people start thinking there's
les peuples vont penser qu' il n'y a
nothing in their account, for their currency, the
rien sur le compte son son sa monnaie la
currency will collapse. And so
monnaie va s'effondrer et donc
today I think he's
aujourd'hui je pense qu'il en est
perfectly aware of this.
parfaitement conscient
The systems, I think the
les systèmes je pense que le le le pr le
Japanese Prime Minister is also
premier ministre japonais en est aussi
aware of this. It's been going on for twenty years, he's been in office for
conscient ça fait vingt ans que ça dure
20 years, but who's been printing money? It's been
ça fait 20 ans qu'il est mais qui fait
years since there's been growth, and we
ans qu'il n'a pas eu de croissance et on
're rich. As the
est riche à en
ultimate weapon to restart
arme suprême pour pour faire repartir
the economy, Mr. Berneau has been leading us on
l'économie monsieur berneau nous balade
for five years. We say, "I'm going to
depuis cinq ans nous disons je vais
make things beautiful, lower unemployment thanks to
faire beau ce baisser le chômage grâce à
my quantitative easing." Very well, that  That's false.
mes quantitative easing très bien que
We can clearly see that he hasn't
c'est faux on voit très bien qu'il n'a
restarted the machine. We can clearly see that
pas relancé la machine on voit très bien
today we're facing the
qu'aujourd'hui on est face à les etats
United States. It's a drug addict
unis c'est un c'est un drogué
with a lone hand who's taking
avec une perte dans le bras qui se prend
4 billion a day of cabbage, that's all.
4 milliards par jour de chou c'est tout
Mr. Verrier, what do you think,
monsieur verrier est ce que vous pensez
key, is the predatory behavior of the
clé le comportement prédateur des états
United States in their foreign policy? A
unis sur leur politique extérieure un
cycle of predatory behavior in
cycle en comporte prédateur sur
debt issuance will be sustainable without
l'émission de dette sera tenable sans
minor disruptions in other
petites perturbations sur les autres
economies. There are
économies
already disruptions in
il ya déjà des perturbations soient
this economy. It's not for nothing that
cette économie est pas pour rien que le
Brazil is
brésil est en train de prendre des
also taking measures to limit the inflow
mesures aussi pour limiter les entrées
of American capital because
de capitaux américains parce qu'une
part of it is obviously fleeing the
partie de skis et crée évidemment fui
United States. The United States has the
les états unis etats unis ont la monnaie
world's reserve currency, which gives them the
de réserve mondiale dont qui ont des
ability to do things we won't have in the
facilités à faire des choses qu'on
same way.
n'aura pas l'aura pas de la même façon
They also export part of their
qu'ils exportent aussi en partie leur
inflation.
leur inflation
But what's interesting in all this is that we're
mais ce qui est intéressant là dedans
facing numerous
c'est qu'on est face à de nombreuses
bubbles:
bulles
[Music]
[Musique]
monetary bubble, asset bubble,
monétaire bulle des actifs l'huile
bond oil that only rests on  On
obligataire qui ne repose que sur la
confidence, 5 for the moment and
confiance 5pour moment et de la
confidence always the system holds this
confiance toujours le système tient ce
amazing trade when we talk about arms,
trade étonnante quand on parle de bras
the gibbons 10, like just anything, have
les gibbons 10 comme juste n'importe
united, still triple A
quoi s'est uni soit toujours triple a
for several rating agencies. I
pour plusieurs agences de notation je me
use a bunch of rating agencies that have
sers un paquet des agences de notation
circumvented in such a desperate situation.
ont contourné dans une situation aussi
Confidence is there, and indeed,
la confiance est là et effectivement
as it lasts, we have policies, in
comme ça dure on a des politiques en
fact, what they  They say it's not a big deal,
fait ce qu'ils disent bat pas très grave
well, we printed 2 billion a day on the
bon on a imprimé 2 milliards par jour au
market, you see, it's not a huge amount, but let
marché voit on pas des masses mais
's try three times in four,
essayons trois essais en quatre
now Japan, 10 times in eight.
maintenant le japon 10 essais en huit
The problem is that confidence and
le problème c'est que la confiance et
binary options, there are some, there aren't, it's
les binaires y en a il y en a pas c'est
not about confidence this Monday, then Tuesday, a little bit on
pas chez confiant ce lundi puis mardi un
Wednesday, then a lot, I
petit peu de mercredi puis beaucoup je
say no, really, we're like in
dis non vraiment on est en train comme
those children's games where the
dans ces jeux pour enfants où ça les
little pyramids, you take turns removing something
espèces de petites pyramides vous
and
enlever un truc chacun votre tour et
then it holds, it holds, it's like in the movie "Les
puis ça tiens ça tient à ce qu'elle joue
Ch'tis," everything collapses, and that's what's likely
dans les ch'tis tout s'écroule et c'est
to happen by
ça qui risque de se passer à force de
doing whatever we want with currencies, by
faire n'importe quoi sur les monnaies à
doing whatever we want with the
force de faire n'importe quoi sur les
markets. But one day it won't work anymore, indeed, there will be
marchés mais un jour ça marchera plus
a politician
effectivement il va y avoir un politique
who will say, "But it's crazy, it worked
qui va dire mais c'est fou ça a marché
for 25 years, I did just a tiny bit
pendant 25 ans j'en ai fait juste un
more and it didn't
tout petit peu plus et ça n'a plus
work at all anymore," because the day we'll say that we should do
marché du tout car le jour on va se dire
better than them,
qu' il faudrait mieux qu'eux
our salary by converting it to
notre salaire en le convertissant francs
Swiss francs 1, because we'll see people
suisses 1 parce qu'on va voir des gens
who  Things are going to get agitated at the
qui vont s'agiter du côté de la banque
central bank; this is going to pose serious problems.
centrale ça va poser de lourds problèmes
The yen has fallen, certainly the Japanese
il ya le yen a chuté certes les japonais
have lost 20% of their international purchasing power
ont perdu 20% de leur pouvoir d'achat
in just a few
international en quelques en quelques
weeks following the statements.
semaines suite aux déclarations
Indeed, we haven't seen anything yet, but
effectivement on n'a rien vu mais
Mr. Lambert, in the event of a widespread loss of
monsieur lambert en cas de perte de
confidence, what do you think
confiance généralisée à votre avis que
could happen?
peut-il se passer
A collapse of economies? All I've
l'affaissement des économies c'est moi
observed in the past, from the
tout ce que j'ai constaté dans le passé
vantage point I've found myself in, is that
l'occasion des postes d'observation je
economies
me suis trouvée c'est que les économies
function well at
fonctionne bien à des taux de croissance
relatively high and satisfactory growth rates when
relativement élevée satisfaisant lorsqu
they combine increased investment, the
elle conjugue un accroissement de
country's economic activity, and consumption.
le bal du pays et de la consommation
When only consumption
lorsque seule la consommation fonctionne
or only investment is working, we
ou le seul investissement fonctionne on
have periods of mediocre growth,
a des périodes de croissance médiocres
in addition to content. On the other hand, when
en plus de contenu ray en revanche quand
both engines
les deux moteurs ses deux moteurs
work together, the economy
fonctionne de pair et bien l'économie
is on a relatively sustained growth trajectory.
est sur un rythme de croissance
Of course, if we manage to maintain confidence,
bien entendu si on arrive à rester rey
today in most major
aujourd'hui dans la plupart des grands
developed countries, and particularly in the
pays développés et singulièrement dans
other, a confidence that allows for a
l'autre une confiance qui permettent le
return to investment,
retour à l'investissement
which is something that companies
ce que ce que les entreprises ne
absolutely do not practice.  For the moment,
pratique absolument pas pour l'instant
for several reasons,
pour différentes raisons parce
firstly because they lack confidence,
qu'effectivement n'ont pas confiance
and secondly because they don't
n'ont pas confiance et deux parce
necessarily have the means;
qu'elles n'ont pas forcément les moyens
their self-financing rate is
leur taux d'autofinancement est
dramatically low and has plummeted in recent
dramatiquement faibles s'est affaissé
years. If we manage to
depuis quelques années si on arrive à
revive this confidence, I think we can
relancer cette confiance je pense qu'on
reconnect with a certain form of
peut renouer avec une certaine forme de
trust, and this form of trust
confiance et cette forme de confiance
can also be reflected in the fact that
peut se traduire aussi par le fait que
the savings, passed on by people in
les tirelires en passer par les gens en
France in particular, but it's true a bit
france en particulier mais c'est vrai un
everywhere in Europe I think, will be
peu partout en europe je pense
broken. These savings, currently
se casseront alors que ces tirelires
intended to
pour l'instant pour objectif de se
protect against unemployment, haven't been able to
prémunir contre le chômage d'un enfant
speak out. We'll break
de chômage n'a pas pu parler on cassera
the savings, and Rocco Samora believes that once
la tirelire et rocco samora à ce que la
confidence has returned, which will allow for a
confiance est revenue qui permettra le
return to investment,
retour à l'investissement est bien ce
we will finally have
jour là on aura enfin enfin une
stable, relatively vigorous real growth.
croissance réelle stables relativement
But it will no longer be like the growth we've
vigoureuse mais elle ne sera plus un à
seen in
l'image de celles qu'on a connues dans
the past; it will be 2 to 2.5 percent, I
le passé ça sera du 2-2 et demi pourcent
imagine. So, at most, you're talking about
j'imagine donc au maximum vous parlez de
confidence,
confiance
confidence.  What do you
de la confiance qu'est ce que vous
think of the business that Jacques
pensez d'affaires qu'elle jacques
Senez, a phenomenon that has died, remains immense? It
senez phénomène mort on reste immense a
introduced an instant drop in confidence,
introduit une chute de confiance
and I
instantanée instantanée et moi je les
reread them more often. This affair, which has had
relis davantage cette affaire qui a eu
its order of ethics and morality in
sa commande de d'éthique de morale de
our societies currently, and which
nos sociétés actuellement et qui en
results from the fact that every day, every
résulte du fait que tous les jours tous
month, you see a huge scandal.
les mois vous voyez un énorme scandale
What they accepted, however small,
ce qu'ils acceptaient toute petite chose
compared to a hormone a few
par rapport à une hormone il ya quelques
years ago, compared to Goldman Sachs, compared
années par rapport à goldman sachs par
to Morgan Stanley, compared to
rapport à morgan stanley par rapport à
Deutsche Bank, compared to the LIBOR problem,
la deutsch bank par rapport au problème
every day you have somewhere
tous les jours vous avez quelque part
the announcement of a
'l'annonce d'un annahda manquements
profound, fundamental breach of ethics, and
profond fondamental à l'éthique et
ultimately all this no longer affects
finalement tout ça ne touche plus
anyone. It serves only that we are here, we look at
personne sert qu'on est là on regarde
all this with completely
tout ça avec des yeux complètement
jaded eyes without questioning what all
affadi sans s'interroger sur ce que tout
this means. Even if Olivier Delamarche,
ça signifie même si olivier delamarche
Mr. Lambert, spoke of LIBOR, what
monsieur lambert a parlé de du libor
can one tell me about Lebanon
qu'est ce qu'on peut me dire du liban
for anything
pour
else? It is indeed a scandal that
autre chose ça fait un scandale en effet
we have. What was this scandal? Not bad,
qu'on a quel était ce scandale pas mal
not bad.
pas mal étouffé
Ultimately, it was hushed up since it's being talked about less
finalement puisqu'on en parle de moins
and less. A few banks
en moins quelques quelques banques ont
paid a small fine to get
payé une petite amende au passage pour
rid of it,
se débarrasser de la chose
but it's them. It's like everything else, like
mais c'est eux
all these
c'est comme tout c'est comme tous ces
scandals: we talk about them for a few
scandales c'est à dire que on en parle
days, a few
pendant quelques quelques jours quelques
weeks in
semaines
the media. These are things—at least as far as
sur les sur les média cd sont des choses
LIBOR is concerned—that don't directly affect
libor que qui touchent pas directement
people because it's complicated to
les gens parce que c'est compliqué de
understand how they manipulated
comprendre comment ils ont manipulé les
things, and so people
choses et que ça donc les gens oublient
quickly forget. And in fact, these are scandals involving
vite et en fait ces décès des scandales
tens and hundreds of billions, settled discreetly
dizaines et des centaines de milliards
with a
et qui sont réglés en sous main avec une
small fine. Mr. Bernier, what surprises me
petite amende monsieur monsieur bernier
in all this is that we're surprised. For
moi moi ce qui m'étonne dans tout ça
thirty years we've been in
ça fait trente ans on est rentré dans
a very clear ideology
une idéologie très clair
of ultra-liberalism or libertarianism,
d'ultra libéralisme ou de libertarisme
which basically says there's an
qui consiste à dire en gros il ya une
invisible hand of the market, which, above all, I
main invisible du marché qui surtout je
want to say—but wait—only has
veux dire mais attendez n'ayez comme
the personal behavior of being
seul le comportement personnel d'être
selfish, and we're not told...  The point
égoïste et on nous dit pas la peine
of having ethical guidelines or a
d'avoir des repères éthiques ou d'un
meal, whether you're a Gaullist or not, it'll be fine,
repas vous soyez gaulliste ça va bien se
but this rule, his rule, isn't based
passer mais cette règle la sienne ne
on any ethical criteria. What does it encourage? It encourages
repose sur aucun critère éthique elle
dishonesty, inevitably. In any case, the
malhonnêteté forcément en tout cas la
condition is that you can tell yourself, "
condition est que vous pouvez vous dire
My goal isn't to be honest, my goal is that no one
mon but n'est pas d'être honnête mon but
knows I'm being dishonest,"
est qu'on ne sache pas que je suis mal
which is very different. So
honnête ce qui est très différent donc à
every time you think you can
chaque fois vous pensez que vous allez
be dishonest without getting caught,
pouvoir être malhonnête sans vous faire
you do it because that's
prendre vous le faite puisque c'est ça
your criterion. Try it against the Duke
votre critère essai en contre au duc
Times, where Enron is found, and
times et à qui on retrouve du enron et à
every time, over the past ten years, it's strange
chaque fois en dix ans passés bizarre
that these companies, we realize they don't care about
que ces boîtes quand même on se rend
us, and the same goes
compte qu'elle se foutent de nous et
for the banks. And yet,
pareil pour les banques et quand même
logically, when you
qu'en conséquence logique quand on
look in detail,
regarde dans le détail
you realize that all the
on se rend compte que toutes les
people who are slightly
personnes qui sont un petit peu
implicated, with a few scandals
incriminé avec quelques scandales
behind them, have exactly the same
derrière eux ils ont exactement le même
background. We always find
parcours on retrouve toujours des gens
very high-ranking people in finance, we
très hauts placés dans la finance on
always find people who have gone through
retrouve toujours des gens passer par
institutions of power. I'm in
les institutions de pouvoir je suis en
green, what do you think? Is it  Do
vert qu'est ce que vous en pensez est ce
you think there's a real
que vous pensez qui a réellement
attraction at higher levels
une attraction à des niveaux supérieurs
to cover up the scandals that
pour se couvrir des scandales qui nous
have allowed us to reach a certain level
ont permis d'atteindre un certain niveau
of responsibility?
de responsabilité
These people, who are part of the fear
ces personnes qui font partie de la peur
class as you say, simply have the
classe comme vous dites ont simplement
power to make
les l'objet d'un pouvoir qui permettent
significant ethical breaches,
des entorses à l'éthique significative
but there are others at lower levels.
mais il y en a d'autres à des niveaux
I don't think it's
subalternes je pense pas que ce soit
limited to a segment of the population.
limité à à une partie de la population
The problem is that there are 50 without proof,
le problème 50 sans preuve que plus
meaning it's become
c'est à dire que c'est devenu d'une
commonplace. So, they know this leads to a
grande banalité alors savent ça entraîne
certain
le passage dans des sectes certain
number of people joining cults, people who no longer believe in
nombre de gens qui ne croient plus à
anything, so they rush towards
rien donc qui se précipitent vers des
cults or religious extremism.
sectes ou vers des extrémismes religieux
I believe we can't
moi je crois qu'on va pas pouvoir
continue to survive this way. I have a somewhat
continuer à survivre de cette façon j'ai
crazy idea: for me,
une idée un peu folle pour ma part
survival is about recreating a
survivre c'est un grossiste à recréer un
minimum of ethics from this liberalism that
minimum d'éthique de ce libéralisme qui
is without faith or law,
est sans foi ni loi
and that we need to establish rules of
et qu'il faut donner des règles de
conduct. So how do we create this
conduite alors comment le créer ce code
ethical code? Well, by bringing together a
éthique et bien en faisant se réunir un
number of people,
certain nombre de gens
each representing a different school of
représentatifs chacun d'un courant de
thought.  The human race, including the
pensée de l'espèce humaine se dire les
major monotheistic religions (
grandes religions monothéistes le
Buddhism, Hinduism), the devout,
bouddhisme l'hindouisme le grand croyant
agnostics, freethinkers, and
les agnostiques les libres penseurs les
Freemasons, perhaps adding a
francs maçons en y ajoutant peut-être
few cheeses, a few Nobel
quelques fromages quelques prix nobel de
Peace Prizes, and a few Nobel Prizes in
la paix quelques prix nobel
science, must
scientifiques il faut faire en sorte de
create a kind of council. If a limited
créer un espèce de con s'il entre des
number of respected people enter,
gens respectés en nombre
as much as possible, so that
limité autant que faire se peut pour que
their work is effective, a council that makes
leurs travaux soit efficace qui fasse
each of the seven billion individuals on
chacun des sept milliards d'individus de
the planet feel represented by one of
la planète se sente représentée par l'un
them. And it would require that, through a
d'entre eux et il faudrait que par une
kind of spontaneous outpouring—you
espèce de jaillissement spontanée vous
see the difficulty of the operation—this
voyez la difficulté de l'opération ce
council, this conclave, lays down the tablets of
concile ce conclave et met les tables de
the law of liberalism, that is to say,
la loi du libéralisme c'est à dire
four or ten pages of great
quatre pages 10 pages d'une grande
scope, definitively condemning unjust
portée sur condamnant définitivement les
enrichment,
l'enrichissement sans cause insolente
child trafficking, and
nature la traite des enfants
child labor, so that
le travail des enfants de façon à ce que
children enter the workforce only when
les enfants arrivent au travail le jour
they have acquired a minimum of
où ils ont acquis un minimum d'autonomie
intellectual autonomy. It definitively condemns
intellectuelle condamne définitivement
inequalities between men and women. And so, we
les inégalités hommes femmes et c'est
all have these tablets of the law without  The spirit, in a
on les a tous sans l'esprit d'une
way, they aren't codified, and
certaine façon elles sont pas codifié et
I dream, I fantasize about a conclave
moi je rêve je fantasme sur un conclave
of people of this nature, of this caliber, who
de gens de cette nature de cette qualité
developed them. So I'm actually working on it
qui les élaboré alors j'y travaille en
with UNESCO, with an association called
fait avec unesco avec une association
the Fraternity of Abraham,
qui s'appelle la fraternité d'abraham
perhaps with the Institut de
peut être avec sûrement de l'institut de
France, and I haven't given up hope of
france et je ne désespère pas de réussir
organizing such a meeting sometime in
à organiser une telle réunion dans le
I hope you haven't connected
je n'espère pas vous avez branché hélas
with Wayne, unfortunately. You were
pas sur wayne là vous allez vous avez
talking about Freemasonry, why
parlé de franc maçonnerie pourquoi
put Freemasons around a
mettre des francs-maçons autour d'une
table? Because their training is a
table parce que les formations sont une
way of thinking that shouldn't be
forme de pensée que qui ne faut pas
neglected. I'm not into
négliger moi je suis pas les coups
Freemasonry, but it so happens that I was
francs maçons mais il se trouve que
invited to give a lecture
j'étais invité à faire une conférence
in front of, I don't remember, El Gran Torino
devant je ne sais plus et el gran torino
and Franck Pellerot,
et franck pellerot orient
on economic warfare, after which
sur la guerre économique
I attended a
à la suite de laquelle j'ai assisté un
cocktail party of this obedience, and I
cocktail de cette obédience et j'ai
found the atmosphere of this lodge
trouvé le climat de cette loge
warm and friendly. Hello, it's a
chaleureux sympathique bonjour c'est une
way of thinking that doesn't shock me.  I'm not
forme de pensée qui ne me choque pas que
part of it because I didn't want to
je n'en fais pas partie parce que je
benefit from it,
n'ai pas voulu me faire des bienfaits d
but there you have it. So I wouldn't want to neglect
mais voilà donc je ne voudrais négliger
any form of contemporary thought,
aucune forme de pensée contemporaine
including the people represented at this
dont les les personnes représentées à ce
conclave. You're talking about roundtables on the
conclave vous parlez de table ronde sur
internet. We're aware of an
internet nous sommes conscients d'un
organization called the Bilderberg Group. What
organisme qui s'appelle les bilderberg
can you tell us
ce qu'est ce que vous pouvez nous dire
about the Beagles? Berck, the town of Berck, is it
sur les beagles berck ville de berck
like the Trilateral Commission, like Davos? They're a kind of reputable
c'est comme la trilatérale comme davos
club where you can find
ce sont des espèces de club
major
de bon aloi ou retrouver des grands
international bankers, big breasts, and
banquiers internationaux des gros seins
top business leaders of all kinds—
des grands chefs d'entreprises de toute
industrial and service-oriented.
nature industrielle de service
I think the media are present at
je pense que les médias sont présents à
these kinds of meetings. In some, I
ce genre de réunions dans certaines je
think so. The town of Bern has held a
pense oui les villes de berne a fait
thousand Merckx meetings. Will it
mille merckx est ce que ça va inscrire
massively register the thousand? The mayor, I don't remember
massivement le mil le maire je ne sais
anymore. I must have participated once or twice a
plus j'ai dû y participer ou de deux
very long time ago.
fois il ya très longtemps
As for the Trilateral Commission, I don't feel
ainsi qu'est la trilatérale je me sens
guilty about, how to
pas pour autant coupable de quelques
say, having shared
comment dire d'avoir partager des
shameful secrets. It's very
secrets honteux c'est une grande
simple. So you have here
simplicité vous avez là donc des chefs
business leaders, grand banquets,
d'entreprise des grands banquets des
major financiers...  Politicians
grands financiers des hommes politiques
arrive with their credo of
ils arrivent avec leur credo d'un
liberalism,
libéralisme
they talk at length for two or
il on parle abondamment pendant deux ou
three exhausting days, and leave having
trois jours épuisant repartent en ayant
engraved
gravé dans un espèce que dans un espèce
the modalities of this liberalism on some kind of hard drive. So,
de disques durs les modalités de ce
it
libéralisme voilà donc ça améliore
slightly improves the functioning of these
légèrement le fonctionnement de ces
liberalisms, alas, not enough to
libéralisme hélas pas suffisamment pour
avoid the excesses we just discussed.
éviter les excès dont on vient de parler
So let's not give
donc ne donnons pas une importance
excessive importance to these kinds of meetings.
excessive à ce genre de rencontres
The striking advance, I mean,
d'avancé l'avancé frappant je veux dire
going in this direction, nothing. I participated in
aller dans ce sens rien j'ai participé
a completely different experience in Nantes. In
une expérience tout à fait à nantes à
Davos, one day, the president of Davos, the
davos un jour le président davos le
creator,
créateur
called me and told me, Bernard Curé, to create
m'a appelé et m'a dit bernard curé créer
a group of what we will call the
un groupe de ce qu'on appellera les
Academic Lieders, on the occasion of
académiques lieders à l'occasion
the next
d'approcher la prochaine réunion de
Davos meeting. It will consist of the presidents of the 15
davos il s'agira des présidents des 15
largest universities in the world.
plus grandes universités mondiales
And so I was very flattered by his
et alors j'étais très flatté de son
initiative. I read that, as president
parti j'ai lu tant que c'est président
of the École Polytechnique, he did indeed bring
de l'école polytechnique il a fait venir
fifteen presidents of
effectivement quinze présidents de
major educational institutions to
grandes institutions d'enseignement à
Davos. GT2, general rapporteur of the group,
davos gt2 rapporteur général du groupe
and  He told us, "Well, listen, prepare
et nous a dit bah écoutez préparer moi
a message for humanity." So we locked ourselves away
un message pour l'humanité alors on
for 48 hours.
s'est enfermés pendant 48 heures
I tried to write in
j'essayais de rédiger en anglais
broken English. It's a synthesis of your
balbutiant elle est la synthèse de vos
work, and we actually drafted
travaux et on a effectivement élaborer
a four- or five-page message that
un message de quatre ou cinq pages qui
covered the themes I just
reprenait les thèmes que je viens
mentioned:
d'évoquer sur le mont travail des
child labor, gender equality, the
enfants l'égalité hommes-femmes la
elimination of illicit enrichment,
suppression des enrichissements selon
etc., plus a few other
etc plus quelques autres
messages on education and the training
messages sur l'éducation la formation
of men in general. We took all of that
des hommes en général on a amené tout ça
to Mr. Claude Fabre, the director of
à monsieur claude fabre directeur de
Davos, who put it in a drawer and
davos qui a rangé sa dans un tiroir
closed it at Clide, to our super
qu'il a fermé à clide à notre super
faction, and who told us, "No, Davos didn't like a
factions et qui nous a dit non davout
message." So there you have it, there are no
s'aimait pas de message donc voilà il
messages within these
n'y a pas de message danser dans ces
structures. There are simply a kind of
structures il ya simplement des espèces
near-consensus that transforms into a
de près consensus qui se transforme en
more pronounced consensus at the end of the
consensus plus accentuée à l'issue des
meetings. I see you
réunions sus de la marche je vois
smiling,
sourire
yes, because all these meetings
oui parce que ce oui toutes ces réunions
are just for empty promises.
c'est fait pour
Nothing ever comes of them, just like the G20, just like
rien sorti comme le g20 pareil
the meetings of the...  The IMF is the same, it
comme les réunions du fmi pareil il en
never gets anything out of it. We get
ai jamais rien sorti on a des
sensational declarations, but Ms.
déclarations fracassantes mais mme
Lagarde or someone
lagarde ou
else says nothing.
ou autre
So I'd say it's business as usual.
avec le rien dedans donc je dirais que
We're being led astray
c'est comme d'habitude on est emmené
today.
aujourd'hui c'est
I said it last week on BFM.
j'ai dit la semaine dernière sur bfm de
Anyway, the sheep have to
toute façon il faut que les moutons se
stay quiet so we can
tiennent tranquilles pour qu'on puisse
bury them. We have to
les tombes
give them, we have to
les il faut il faut donner il faut
give them a little lullaby
donner une petite musique
so we can
qui endort aux moutons pour qu'on puisse
shear them peacefully. So that's what's being done. That's what's being
les tondre tranquillement donc c'est ce
done when
qui est fait c'est ce qui est fait quand
we give figures that are false, completely
on donne des chiffres qui sont faux et
false. We're talking about unemployment figures,
archi faux c'est des chiffres du chômage
growth figures,
des chiffres de la croissance des
figures... we do it
chiffres de
constantly. Speaking
l'ons le fait en permanence en parlant
of unemployment figures, the figures from
des chiffres du chômage les chiffres de
Friday...
vendredi
hiccup... in the United States, a dismaying thing is that we
sur la téte hic sur les états unis un
continue to do
consternant c'est qu'on continue à
exactly the same thing, as we have for
exactement comme com comme depuis
several months, even several
plusieurs mois et même et même plusieurs
years, making
années
people disappear. There are
ont fait disparaître des gens il ya six
630,000 Americans who
cent trente mille américains qui tout
suddenly disappeared. That is to say, we
d'un coup ont disparu c'est à dire qu'on
lower the voter turnout rate.  This is
fait baisser le taux de participation à
possible given the labor force's low level of unemployment, which has never
la possible à la population active qui
been so low. And
n'a jamais été aussi bas et
if you compare that to the average labor force
si vous remettez ça sur les la moyenne
participation rate,
de taux de participation à la populace à
if you compare that to
la population active si vous remettez ça
the average today, there are 11.6%
sur la moyenne aujourd'hui il ya 11 6 %
unemployed in the United States. Okay, so
de chômeurs aux états unis d'accord donc
if you take the figure after expanding it,
si vous prenez le chiffre après étendu
which is what they call the EU-
qui est ce que ce qu'ils appellent la
6 component—that is, people
composante eu 6 c'est à dire les gens
who work a few hours per share
qui travaillent quelques heures par part
per month—you end up
par mois et sert à vous retrouver
with an unemployment rate close to
avec un taux de chômage qui est proche
10.9%, or rather, 1 in 5, still, right?
des 10 9% enfin numérique 1 sur 5 quand
And then when you look at
même hein et après quand vous allez dans
the details, you see that unemployment
le détail vous apercevez que le chômage
has never lasted so long. You
a jamais duré aussi longtemps vous
see that there have never been so many
apercevez qui a jamais eu autant de deux
fixed-term contracts,
contrats de 2 à durée déterminée de
temporary contracts, etc. You see
contrats d'intérim etc vous apercevez
that
que on a
since 2008, we have created 4 million
depuis 2008 on a créer 4 millions
jobs in the United States for those over
d'emplois aux états unis sur les plus de
55,
55 ans
and that, on the other hand, for those under 55, that is,
et que en revanche la partie moins de 55
young Americans,
ans c'est à dire les jeunes américains
we have lost three million.  Jobs are disappearing,
là on a perdu trois millions d'emplois
but nobody seems bothered, and we keep
mais ça choque personne et on continue à
telling you, "Oh, but the United States is
vous dire ah mais les états unis sont
full of
pleines
reindustrialization." We look at the
réindustrialisation et on regarde les
figures, and we realize that we're laying off
chiffres et là on s'aperçoit qu'on vire
everyone every year in the manufacturing sector. We
tous les jeux tous les ans dans le la
live for
partie industrie et manufactures on vit
a month, every month, we lay people off,
un mois tous les mois on vire des gens
and we tell you, "But we've
et on vous dit mais l'avons
reindustrialized!" No, that's false. And
réindustrialiser non c'est faux et
today, we haven't
aujourd'hui on est on a on n'a pas
hired a single person. In other words,
engagé un seul type c'est à dire le
quantitative easing hasn't produced any
quantitative easing n'a pas produit
decrease in unemployment at all.
absolument pas de baisse du chômage
That's completely false, and that's part
c'est faux archi faux et ça fait partie
of those figures. So, we're pulling the same trick on you,
de ces chiffres alors on vous fait la
I'm sure we're doing the same thing with
même je vous fait le même coup sûr sur
housing in the United States, where
le logement aux etats-unis où les
banks are seizing
banques séquestre les
the homes they've confiscated to
les habitations qu'elles ont qu'elles
prevent the
ont saisi pour que pour empêcher le
market from continuing to fall. So, they end up
marché de continuer à baisser donc ils
with stocks of
se retrouvent avec des stocks
unsold properties today, due to
aujourd'hui de d'invendus dia de la
bank retention of assets. And
rétention bancaires sur les actifs et
obviously,
évidemment et et
everything is like that. We have a
et tout est comme ça c'est à dire que on
knack for it, clearly.  We wonder
a on a le chic visiblement on se demande
if analyst firms sometimes
si quelquefois les bureaux d'analystes
do their job. Sometimes, they even
font leur boulot silice quelquefois
try
aussi cherchent ici
to compare figures here,
s'amuse un peu à confronter les chiffres
because, well,
parce que
regarding
parce que c'est c'est juste concernant
the precise figures, the analyst firms aren't doing
le chiffre précis les bureaux d'analysé
their job. Are the
ne font pas leur travail est ce que les
journalists behind them
journalistes derrière
now also not doing their job? But that's not their
maintenant non plus mais c'est pas leur
job; it's primarily the job of
boulot c'est le boulot d'abord d'aider
analyst firms, strategists,
des bureaux d'analystes des stratégistes
and economists to do it. Then the
et économistes de le faire après le
journalist is there to get the
journaliste il est là pour pour le faire
strategists to say this, but it's not
dire aux stratégies ce mais c'est pas
their job to go looking for that.
son boulot d'aller d'aller chercher ça
They could do it, but they don't. There were
il pourrait le faire mais il le fait pas
inconsistencies everywhere. That is to
il avait des incohérences partout c'est
say, we are
à dire qu'on est en train de regarder
also looking at the inconsistencies that perpetuate the
aussi les incohérences qui assurent le
myth of
sur le le mythe de l'indépendance
American energy independence. If you look at shale
énergétique américaine si vous regardez
gas production,
les la production de gaz de schiste
you realize that
exter vous apercevez qu'on est en train
you're being sold a load of nonsense that will
de vous vendre une salade qui va être
probably be very indigestible. So,
probablement très indigeste voilà donc
simply put, we need to look into
mais simplement il faut se pencher sur
things, we need to try to work.  Just a little bit, that's
les choses il faut essayer de bosser un
Paris for you, it's tiring, but you're in pain.
ça c'est paris c'est fatigant mais vous
You're talking about energy transition,
avez mal vous parlez de ddn d'énergie
Mr. Lambert. How do you plan to
monsieur lambert comment pensez-vous
finance the
dans ces conditions financer la
energy transition in France, in
transition énergétique en france en
Europe, and worldwide under these conditions? This whole
europe et dans le monde toute cette
pyramid of government debt has
pyramide de dettes des gouvernements qui
n't helped its citizens finance
ont pas aidé leurs citoyens à financer
this transition. The financing of
cette transition le financement des
energy imports has always been
importations énergétiques s'est toujours
done through exports; I know, that was
fait par les exportations je sais leur a
their raison d'être from the
été d'ailleurs leur raison d'être au
start. The
départ la première balle en sus les
first balance of trade,
premières balance du commerce extérieur
40-50 years ago, was a very simple trade balance. On
il ya 40 50 ans étaient des balances
one side, there were
simplicité il y avait d'un côté les
energy
importations énergétiques
and pre-final imports, and then exports of
et préfinale et puis des exportations
products intended to cover those imports. So,
produits destinés à couvrir ses
gradually,
première balle ans progressivement à
starting in 1962, a
partir de 62 d'ailleurs de 1962 une
second balance of trade in
deuxième balance des échanges de
industrial products was added to this first balance. And so,
produits industriels et un tel enseigne
the weight of exports went
que le poids des exportations est passé
from a few percent of the
de quelques pour cent de la richesse
national wealth of the GNP to 20% by the 1970s.
nationale du pnb à 20% dès les années 70
Since then, as international trade has
depuis comme le commerce international a
continued to grow,
continué à croître et à faire en sorte
a third  This balance is added to the
qu'une troisième balance s'ajoute aux 2
first two, or even a fourth. We are now at
premières voire même une quatrième on en
approximately
est à environ
40% of the weight of international trade in our wealth. This
dans notre richesse de l'ordre de 40%
means that, on average, we work
dire que tout en moyenne on travaille
almost one day out of two for exports and one day out of two for
presque un jour sur deux pour
imports.
l'exportation pour pour l'importation
So, all of this has always been
donc tout ceci c'est toujours jusqu'à
resolved in this way, for us
présent résolu de cette façon pour nous
French in particular, with a surplus
français en particulier avec un excédent
in our foreign trade.
de notre commerce extérieur c'est
Incidentally, to make a
d'ailleurs par don de faire une
brief aside, it is this
parenthèse c'est cet accroissement
voracious increase in international trade, which
boulimique du commerce international qui
has grown by about 7% more than
a crû d'environ 7% de plus que la
global wealth in real terms. On the
richesse mondiale en termes réels
ground, we have an enormous 27%. That means
terrain at-on énorme 27% ça veut dire
per year, that means a doubling in ten
par an ça veut dire le doublement en dix
years. This, moreover, means that the share
ans ce qui d'ailleurs à ces produits
of
terre le doublement de la part des
international trade in global wealth has doubled. This is what led me
échanges internationaux dans la richesse
to develop this theory of
m'a conduit à élaborer cette théorie de
economic warfare, because it is through these
la guerre économique parce que c'est par
exports and
le biais de ses exportations et de ses
imports that we have spread the virus of
importations qu'on a propagé le virus de
competitiveness, which itself has driven
la compétitivité qui a lui-même entraîné
all the economies that participated
toutes les économies qui ont participé
in this significant growth of 5-6%
dans cette croissance importante 5 6%
during  20 years, then two enemies, 3%
pendant 20 ans puis de deux ennemis 3%
following, and that's what allowed this
suite et c'est ce qui a permis cet
enrichment, but what about the
enrichissement moyens mais qu'a eue la
cruelty and the arrogance of letting considerable
cruauté et l'ars de de laisser subsister
income disparities persist,
des écarts de super u de revenus
the financing of the
considérable le financement de la
energy transition in France, what do
transition énergétique la france qu'est
you think of the wishes?
ce que vous en pensez des voeux est-ce
Could you also explain to Hunter
que vous pouvez aussi expliqué à hunter
the price signal? What does
le signal prix qu'est ce que veut dire
the price signal mean in terms of
le signal prix pour pour au niveau du
financing
financement
itself? And this is a topic
lui même dire et c'est un sujet
we talk about a lot:
on en parle beaucoup le patrimoine en
France's assets are worth 13 trillion euros. I
france est de 13 mille milliards d'euros
think we have enough to finance
pense qu'on a de quoi financer des
energy transitions. We know that it won't
transitions énergétiques ont ce que ça
start until, indeed, at
ne démarrera pas tant que en effet au
level 2, in terms of prices, you have
niveau 2 au niveau des prix vous n'avez
a price for bread, a bus, a
pas un prix du pain du bus un prix du
liter of gasoline at 3 or 4 euros. And then, don't worry,
litre d'essence à 3 ou 4 euros et relais
when it happens—and it will happen
quand ça va arriver et ça va arriver
much faster than we think—
beaucoup plus vite qu'on ne le pense
you will inevitably need to
vous allez avoir forcément besoin de
convert your economy a bit. On the
convertir un peu votre votre économie
contrary, I also want to say
anwar un contrario j'ai envie de dire
it's an important topic. It's
aussi c'est un sujet important c'est
good to think about it a little. It's not an
bien d'y réfléchir un peu c'est pas le
urgent matter, I swear. Jean Cerner, faced with
sujet urgent je jure jean cerner face à
a pyramid of debt that is going to collapse,
une pyramide de dettes qui va s'écrouler
we are facing a European currency that
on est face à une monnaie européenne qui
is on the verge of collapse, and nobody knows
est subclaquant tu dont personne ne sait
how we'll get out of it without
comment on en sort sans avoir des dégâts
colossal damage.  I think that's where we'll need to
colossaux là dedans mais je pense que
put a certain amount of energy,
mettre un certain nombre d'énergies et
thought, and reflection to build on what was
de d2 et de réflexion pour rebondir sur
said earlier.
ce qui a été dit tout à l'heure aussi
I also wanted to make a couple of
j'avais envie de faire deux trois de
minor remarks on
trop petites remarques de niveau
different levels, concerning ethics and
différent au niveau de l'éthique et au
behavior. What strikes me is that when we're
niveau du comportement
also in an era where there's been a
est aussi dans une époque où il ya eu un
gigantic weakening of
affaiblissement gigantesque à 22 des
collective values—
valeurs collectives
very amusing, forty years ago you
très amusant il ya quarante ans vous
had battles fought roughly
aviez des combat qui a été mené en gros
between a
entre une pensée on pourrait dire de
right-wing Catholic ideology and a left-wing
droite catholique 1 face à une gauche
communist ideology, very different in
communiste diamants très différente en
appearance but which, in any case, emphasized
apparence mais qui de toute façon portée
the collective—we realize that both have
du collectif en s'aperçoit que les deux
collapsed, that they've been
se sont se sont écroulés que ça a été
replaced by nothing but an
remplacé par rien si ce n'est pas une
ideology of individualism: act well,
idéologie de l'individualisme agir bien
be selfish, think only of yourself, everything will be fine. Just
soyez égoïste penser qu'à vous ça se
like in '89, we saw the
passera bien tout comme en 89 on a vu
collapse of a world where only
s'écrouler un monde où on avait mis que
the collective was valued and
du collectif est plus du tout des
individual freedoms were completely eliminated. Well, here we are...
libertés individuelles bah là on est en
Seeing it collapse, probably
train de voir s'écrouler probablement
my good friend, is nothing but
mon bon ami que de la liberté
individual freedom and no longer any sense of
individuelle et plus du tout le
community. Being a beggar is what you
collectif être mendient ce qui vous
lack to build connections and to become a professional, to build a
manque pour faire lien et pour faire un
society. I don't have the
pro faire société moi j'ai pas la
answer, but this lack is
réponse mais bon ce manque là et quand
undoubtedly a structuring factor in what's
même sans doute structurants dans ce qui
happening today. Second thought:
se passe aujourd'hui deuxième réflexion
on the
sur le
ground, always more, one step at a time, growth
sol toujours plus un pas la croissance
was rapid, always more, always more
allait rapidement toujours plus toujours
goods, always more
plus de biens toujours plus de
growth. There's also a
croissance il y aussi un aspect
financial aspect, always more
financier a vraiment toujours plus
money, always higher
d'argent toujours plus de hautes
salaries. And when you see the
rémunérations et quand on voit les les
evolution of
évolutions des rémunérations des
executive compensation in large companies, it's
dirigeants des grandes entreprises c'est
quite fabulous. For 80 years,
quand même assez fabuleux pendant 80 ans
I've had ratios of 120 to 40 between the
j'ai eu des ratios de 1 20 à 40 entre le
CEO and the company's business salary,
pdg et le salaire affaires de
so suitable for 400, but there are companies, that is to
l'entreprise donc apte à 400 mais il ya
say, going from
des boîtes c'est à dire et à 8000 passer
quite cleanly to 8000, it's madness. And it's
du assez proprement du délire et c'est
something that, in my opinion,
quelque chose qui à mon sens atteint
really strikes at the very foundations of
vraiment les fondements mêmes du
capitalism and darkens its
capitalisme et de sombres de son
acceptance. So I hope there will
acceptation donc j'espère qu'il y aura
also be developments in this area.  It's
aussi là dessus des évolutions qui
probably more brutal than I would have liked,
seront sans doute plus brutal que ce que
but we see that when you
j'aurais souhaité mais on voit que quand
want to impose a 75% tax rate on
on veut mettre un taux à 75% sur des
salaries that
rémunérations qui déjà
are already exorbitant for Bondy employees,
sont délirantes pour du salarié bondy
it's unconstitutional, it's not possible.
inconstitutionnelles c'est pas possible
Perhaps we'll have to
pas faudra peut-être arriver à les
limit them a bit more, a bit more
limiter un peu plus un peu plus
drastically, at the level of, I repeat,
brutalement au niveau je répète des
employees of very large companies. A
salariés des très grosses entreprises 1
third point, also on the political front, which I hadn't addressed before, is that we need to think
un troisième point sur le sol politique
more about
pense qu'il faut qu'on réfléchisse plus
our institutions. We have
aussi à nos institutions alors dire on a
institutions that are obviously
des institutions qui sont évidemment
those of the Fifth Republic,
celles de la cinquième qui ont été
built in
bâties
1958, during the "thirty glorious years,"
1958 donc pendant les trente glorieuses
institutions that work
qui sont des institutions qui marche
very well when it comes to distributing 6%
très bien quand il faut distribuer 6 %
growth in the country. We realize that with
croissance dans le pays on s'aperçoit
3% growth, all they can
quand à 3% de croissance ça ne sait
do is create debt
faire qu'une chose c'est de la dette
for 30 years, and when we reach 0%
pendant 30 ans et quand on arrive à 0%
growth, we realize that
de croissance on se rend compte qu
obviously we can't take on any more debt.
évidemment on peut plus faire de dettes
And when we're told that we're supposed to
et que doit on nous dit qu'on est censé
repay the debts of the last 30
rembourser les dettes des 30 dernières
years, we see...  That we can't manage it, and
années on voit qu'on n'y arrive pas et
this system also carries within it,
ce système porte en lui aussi une
I find, a selection of those elected at the
je trouve d un des élus un de niveau
national level, and of those who are truly in the
national et de ce qu'ils sont vraiment
spotlight. So it's only
sur le devant de la scène donc c'est que
10 or 15% of the total, but there are 900 members of
10 ou 15% du total mais il ya 900
parliament and senators. Well, we think about it
députés et sénateurs ben on réfléchit en
knowing some of them, and the others we don't know.
en connaissant et les autres on l'est on
If I have someone there,
les connaît pas si j'en à seissan là
unfortunately, often in this person, to
malheureusement souvent en sa personne
reach these levels you are
pour arriver à ces niveaux là vous êtes
forced to lie, to be
obligés d'être de mentir d'être
dishonest, well, you
malhonnête de enfin voilà enfin vous
select a few of the
sélectionné quelques par les individus
most perverse individuals because to get elected, to be at the
les plus pervers parce que pour arriver
top ahead of everyone
à être élu être en tête devant tous les
else, frankly, it's still
autres
extremely difficult. It requires a
extrêmement difficile ça demande une
personal commitment that is
implication personnelle qui est
insane, and I think that no one
délirante et je pense que personne
around this table is
autour de cette table n'est prêt
really ready to face it. It's very difficult
vraiment à faire face est très difficile
today to be of service to one's
aujourd'hui d'être au service un peu de
country. Well, in the
son pays bon dans le système de
selection system, you select these
sélection vous sélectionnez ces
individuals, I call them the most perverse. We
individus j'appelle les plus pervers on
realize this from time to time when we shine
s'aperçoit de temps en temps quand on
a spotlight on them.  On some
met un coup de projecteur sur certains
banks by the majority, but still a
banks par la majorité mais quand même un
certain number by Bruce had
certain nombre par bruce avait des
individuals who, by dint of being
individus qui à force d'avoir été
dishonest with their voters,
malhonnête avec leurs électeurs
end up being honest in Bamako,
finissent par être à bama l'honnête tout
period. So we need to
court donc il faut qu'on ait une
reflect on how we sanction them, and
réflexion sur comment on sanctionne et
in this system we realize that we no longer
dans ce système là on s'aperçoit qu'on
sanction Yahoo. What will
ne sanctionne plus yahoo qu'est ce que
Mr. Cahuzac get? Probably not much.
va avoir monsieur cahuzac sans doute pas
We're waiting for
grand chose on attend de la semaine
last week, when they were thinking about
dernière qu'ils pensaient comme à
returning to the National Assembly. We're saying, "Hey, that's still
revenir à l'assemblée on se dit tiens
an
c'est quand même une sanction
interesting sanction." You have this everywhere, the
intéressante vous avez ça partout les
subprime mortgages in the United States. Well, you had
subprimes aux états unis enfin vous avez
thousands or tens of
eu des milliers ou des dizaines de
thousands of false declarations against
milliers de fausses déclarations envers
unemployed people earning a thousand dollars a
des chômeurs qui gagne mille dollars par
month who declared ten thousand last year. No one
mois qui déclare l'an dernier dix mille
was prosecuted. The CEO who
personne n'a été poursuivi le pdg qui a
sank Dexia, aptly named Pierre
coulé dexia quand même bien nommé pierre
Richard, continues to collect his pension
richard continue à percevoir sa retraite
quietly. Hats off to him. Did he consult
tranquillement chapeau est-ce qu'il est
a psychic? And perhaps we should also
venu à quelqu un médium et il faudrait
explain that he
peut-être déjà quand même expliqué qu'il
probably lied when he was
a probablement menti au moment de son
hired, since  I imagine he
embauche puisque j'imagine qu'il a
declared himself competent, but
déclaré qu'il était compétent mais la
subsequent events showed that wasn't entirely the
suite a montré pas c'était pas tout à
case.
fait tout à fait la réalité mais voilà
Anyway, I'm being a bit harsh, but there are more
enfin je suis un peu dur mais il ya plus
sanctions in this system. The
de sanctions dans ce système là les
abuses are significant and
dérives sont son sont importantes et
charming, and obviously not sanctioned. The
charmant non sanctionnée évidemment
financing doesn't work, so the
qu'on finance fonctionne pas bah le
next guy continues. He didn't mention the
suivant il continue en a pas parlé les
bank stress tests. In the middle of these
stress tests des banques au milieu de ce
stress tests for the past four years, he
stress test depuis quatre ans qui nous a
explained to us that Irish banks were
expliqué que les banques irlandaises ça
working really well, that Cypriot banks were working incredibly well,
marchait vraiment bien que les banques
that Dexia was working incredibly well. Where we
que dexia marché drôlement bien où on
see that we've done whatever we want with
voit ça peut nous avons fait n'importe
bank stress tests, and that Boya pressure, that the bear,
banques et que boya pression que l'ours
not so bad, wait for the day you
pas bien grave attendu le jour vous
take a dozen consultants and
allez prendre une dizaine de consultants
tell them – as sad as
vous leur dites fait - as tristesse
a bank, if Hoult Bank gets
d'une banque si la banque hoult aura
five years in prison, I guarantee you
cinq ans de prison je vous garantis que
the stress tests will be of high
le stress tests il va être de grande
quality. He simply laughs to
qualité simplement il rit de vous
show you that the bank was already
montrer que la banque était déjà en
bankrupt. It's often Mr. I
faillite c'est souvent monsieur je
change my mind once on the way to
change mon d'une fois sur le chemin de
the march, MF Global,
la marche mf global
the sanctions,
les sanctions
the mechanism that is  What happened
le mécanisme qu'est ce qui s'est passé
with Mev Global, Jon Corzine, and did he take
avec mev global jon corzine at il pris
reggae advice? What kind of care would you
des conseils reggae qu'est ce qu'un soin
advise her to go to? I'll
conseilleriez qu'elle aille je vous
leave you to leverage
laisse leverage
MF Global. That's the problem with leverage,
mf global c'est le problème du leverage
meaning that at one point
c'est à dire qu'à un moment
you had, if I remember correctly, 35 or 36 times the
vous aviez jeux de mémoire 35 ou 36 de
leverage. At some point
d'effet de levier
you make a
à un moment vous faites vous faites une
mistake and you're screwed. Stop it.
erreur et vous sautez cesser enfin là il
People need to realize this,
faut quand même que les gens se rendent
and Olivier is right, there were no
compte et olivier a raison il n'y a pas
sanctions in 2008. The banks... we
eu de sanctions en 2008 les banques ont
felt the cannonball pass very, very
on a senti le boulet du canon passé pas
close to all of our heads
très très loin de nos têtes à tous à
because of the banks. Did you see a
cause des banques vous avez vu un
change? No, none at all. So we
changement non aucun donc on a continué
happily continued to use almost the
joyeusement a utilisé quasiment les
same leverage. We
mêmes effets de levier on à voir
sometimes see some banks
quelquefois pour certaines banques à
increase their balance sheets. Société
augmenter leurs bilans la société
Générale...
générale
no lessons are learned, so you count...
aucune leçon ne sert donc vous comptiez
and
et
in the same spirit, since
dans le même esprit puisque toute façon
you don't face any sanctions anyway, you
vous n'avez pas de sanction donc vous
can sink a bank, put 25,000
pouvez couler une banque met 25 mille
people out of work,
personnes au chômage
cost the community a few billion, and
coûté quelques milliards à la
you're not sanctioned.
collectivité vous n'êtes pas sanctionné
Why would you want his
donc pourquoi voulez-vous que sa faute
short-term recommendations to be
préconisations à court terme c'est
toughened? It's about toughening
durcir les sanctions à durcir les
sanctions,
sanctions
doing what
faire ce qu'a demandé
Olivier asked for, what we've been demanding for a
olivier ce que nous on réclame depuis
very long time, which is to say, through
depuis très longtemps c'est à dire c'est
banking activity and
par l activité bancaire de l'activité
market activity, bring back a completely
marchés revenir un glass steagal
airtight and
tout à fait tout à fait hermétique et
definitive glass-stealth system. These are all things that aren't being
définitif voilà toutes choses qui ne
done because,
sont ne sont pas fait parce que
ultimately, we realize, and then we're told, "
finalement s'aperçoit alors on nous dit
Yes, England has made the decision,
oui l'angleterre a pris la décision il
England has made the decision for
l'angleterre a pris la décision pour
it won't be done." And
ça ne sera pas fait c'est donc et
today we're talking about it in France.
aujourd'hui on en parle en france
Mr. Hollande, I believe,
monsieur hollande je crois en avait
spoke about it. Apparently, he forgot one of his
parlé visiblement il a oublié un ces
problems, Alzheimer's, I think, early on. So there you have it.
problèmes de l'alzheimer je pense
Because today you have
parce que parce que vous avez
a
aujourd'hui ddv lobby bancaire qui sont
very powerful banking lobby, the banks have banded together,
très puissants les banques se sont
and
regroupés et
today when you ask them for
aujourd'hui quand vous leur demandez
something, they say it because they were
quelque chose il faut le disent parce
saved. And it was in 2008
qu'on les a sauvés et c'était en 2008
that things really needed to be done.
qu'il fallait réellement faire les
Now they're here.  They
choses là maintenant ils sont ici ils
all seem to be in
ont l'impression d'être tous sens en
great shape, and when you
grande forme et quand quand vous leur
ask them something, they say
demandez quelque chose ils vous disent
no. They say no to two out of ten
non ils vous disent non sur deux en dix
years, Yves. If you bother us, we won't lend to
ans yves si vous nous embêter on prête
the economy anymore. It's been quite a while since they stopped
plus à l'économie ça fait déjà un bon
lending to the economy,
moment qu'ils prêtent plus à l'économie
but it doesn't matter, they make you believe it.
mais c'est pas grave ils le font croire
And so, obviously, the minister in question goes into
et donc évidemment le ministre concerné
his office. In ten years, above all, don't
entre dans son bureau en dix ans surtout
bother,
ne vous dérangez pas
the transition is around. He's coming in there,
la transition est autour y rentre
precisely. Ethics, no, I was talking to you earlier about
justement là l'éthique non vous parlais
the political career and
tout à l'heure le parcours politique et
the
les
potential pressures from the financial world.
pressions potentielles du monde
Your career, Mr. Lambert, has
votre parcours monsieur lambert vous a
allowed you to summarize
permis de résumer
your thoughts, your
votre pensée votre
ideas on this, the different levers and
idée sur ce les différents leviers et
recommendations. It's possible to be
préconisations possible d'être dans
present here in your work.
votre ouvrage ici présents est-ce que
Can you give us some avenues to explore, in
vous pouvez nous donner quelques pistes
your opinion, to follow? First, I have to
selon vous à suivre pour d'abord je dois
build our armor to come back to what has just been
faire notre armure pour revenir sur ce
said. Okay, on the
qui vient d'être dit bon sur la
separation of investment banking activities
séparation des activités de banque
and the number of deposits, of
d'affaires et le nombre de dépôts bien
course, we have to get there, we have to
sûr
redo a
il faut t'y venait il faut refaire un
layer of ice. There is, in France, it's
glacis glace il ya là qu'en france c'est
clear that...  that we made a joke about
clair ce qu'on a fait une plaisanterie
bathing attendants on Thursday to finalize its
de garçons de bain jeudi à finaliser ses
activities, they already are
activités elles le sont déjà de toute
anyway, so it's really according to the
façon donc c'est vraiment selon la
general company, it only represents
société générale ça ne représente que 0
0.5,000 military personnel,
5 000 militaires
said its president in front of me. I'm taking a
a dit son président devant je prends une
commission, it's perfectly justified to get me drunk,
commission est tout à fait fondée à me
sir, to tell you, here are seven
saouler à monsieur vous dire voilà sept
shots, the pleasure boating is really there,
tirs la plaisance est vraiment là
pleasant and Dias Honda, well, it doesn't matter
plaisante et dias honda bon peu importe
about individualism, that's a subject that's still much
sur l'individualisme ça c'est un sujet
more important.
quand même beaucoup plus importantes
All current sociological studies
toutes les études sociologiques actuelle
show that indeed there is this
montre qu'effectivement il ya cette
immense return to individualism which is also
immense retour à l'individualisme qui se
reflected in its
traduit d'ailleurs dans son plan
religious plan by the development of
religieux par le développement des
sects, by the development of
sectes par le développement des églises
evangelical churches. One is created every
évangéliques il s'en crée une tous les
two weeks in France. The evangelical churches, it was quite
quinze jours en france les églises
astonishing because everyone makes their own
étonnant par le fait que chacun se fait
religion, taking a
sa religion à sa carte en prenant un
little bit of Catholicism, Judaism,
petit peu de de catholicisme judaïsme
Islam. Everyone
l'islam de chacun se
prepares their ideological propensity.
prépare sa propension
All this is true, is it
tout ceci est vrai est-ce que c'est
extraordinarily dangerous?  What is it that we
extraordinairement dangereux est ce que
give a... I don't believe it.
c'est qu'on donne un je ne le crois pas
We quickly realize, first of all, the return to
on s'est vite d'abord le retour à des
common coercive systems put in place
système coercitif commun mise en place
by people who quickly become
par des gens qui deviennent rapidement
tyrants when, on the contrary, there is too much
des tyrans quand il est au contraire
convergence, as was the
trop de convergence comme ça a été le
case in the Soviet Union and in
cas en union soviétique et dans l'ip
Nazi Germany. Simply, once again,
lait dans l'allemagne nazie simplement
we must frame all of this. It
encore une fois il faut cadrer tout ça
gave him a sense of morality.
lui donnait un sentiment de morale
Beaumont, a somewhat crazy idea, once again,
beaumont idée un peu folle encore une
to create his own tablets of the law.
fois de créer ses tables de la loi
On the level, they
sur le plan
are on the point, on the ethical level,
sont sur le point sur le plan éthique
on the salary gaps. An anecdote:
sur les écarts de salaire une anecdote
when I was myself president of a
quand j'étais moi-même président d'une
company,
entreprise
my salary was 15 times that of the
mon salaire a présenté 15 fois celui du
milk company. Rumor has it I had the
lait la rumeur obtiendra la rémunération
lowest remuneration in the company. A few
la plus faible de l'entreprise quelques
years later, that was in the
années plus tard ça c'était dans les
70s and 80s. A few years later,
années 70 80 quelques années plus tard
in the 90s, it was... because it went up
dans les années 90 c'était car c'est
to 50, 60, 70. So I wrote a
monté à 50 60 70 alors j'ai fait un
long article in the newspaper,
grand article dans le fil rouge et droit
a page, by the way, which never happened again, in which
une page d'ailleurs qu'il n'est plus
I condemned those who...  The
dans lequel je condamnais ceux se ses
gaps of 50, 70, 80, which already seemed
écarts de 50 70 80 qui me paraissaient
too high to me, and Fillon
quand même déjà trop élevé et fillon
had headlined it, and Lambert condemned the
avait titré et lambert condamne l'écart
salary gap of 1 to 70, is indeed
des salaires de 1 à 70 est effectivement
in place between 500 and 1 to 500, even a
en état entre 500 de 1 à 500 voire un
friend today, and without anyone finding fault with it. In a
ami aujourd'hui et sans que personne n'y
way,
trouve à redire d'une certaine façon
it was called the business leaders
c'était appelé les chefs d'entreprise
who benefit from it, how to say, are on
qui en bénéficient comment dire sont sur
another planet, they don't live on
une autre planète ne vivent pas sur
Earth, they don't realize
terre ne se rendent pas compte de
the effect produced by salaries of
l'effet produit par des rémunérations de
this date, eyes that generate, let's say,
cette date yeux qui engendre se dire des
very strong feelings,
sentiments très forts des crispations
very strong tensions at the popular level, and that's
très forte au niveau populaire et c'est
quite natural, and at the level of
bien naturel et au niveau de
the company itself, let's not exhale much,
l'entreprise elle-même exhalons pas mal
even the state, DRAC had done
même l'état drac avait fait des travaux
very interesting work on this, we see and
très intéressant là dessus on y voit et
hear it, but this amnesty is in a way anesthetized,
s'entend mais cette amnistie est d'une
or rather anesthetized,
certaine façon par ou anesthésié plus
earlier by stock options,
tôt par les stock options des
free share distributions, than the
distributions d'actions gratuites que le
wise one who, like at Kiki, only do what makes, who unites, the
sage qui comme au kiki seuls qui font
managers, the
qui solidarise des responsables des
bosses, a certain number of executives, in
patrons un certain nombre de cadres
short, at its end  It's not much, admittedly, there are a
bref à sa fin c'est peu certes il ya
few crumbs given, but anyway, as is the case, when managers
quelques poussières donné mais enfin
start
comme toute façon le cadre se met à
having bosses who earn 100-200 times what they
avoir un patron qui gagnent 100 200 x
earn today, you'll still get that same
ski ce qu'ils gagnent hui vous aurez
feeling that was
ce sentiment là même qui était décrit
very well described by Pléthore du Caire,
très bien par pléthore du caire en
explaining a rather funny phrase: 110.
expliquant une phrase assez rigolote 110
The problem with this isn't so much
dans le problème avec avec ça c'est pas
that bosses have lost
tant que les patrons ont perdu
the respect of their base salaries—well, strictly speaking, that never happens, and they
l'estiment de leurs prix de base bon à
always think the
lampes led basse pense toujours que le
boss is a crook—but they are
patron est un escroc mais ils sont en
losing the respect of senior managers, even
train de perdre l estime des des cadres
first-level executives, who think their
premier niveau qui pensent que leur
boss is, and was, a crook somewhere. What
patron est un et 1 était un escroc à
they want is this
quelque part qu'ils veulent c'est cette
compensation, the slow recovery, knowing that they
rémunération la lente reprise sachant
themselves have
lui-même à des récompenses de plus en
increasingly limited rewards. So, in
plus de plus en plus limitées donc en
any case, it's very destructive
tout cas c'est très destructeur aussi
to the company's image, at least in
sur le sentiment d'entreprise en tout
terms of loss of respect,
cas en terme de perte de respect
which would merit some
qui mériterait quelques analyses
interesting sociological analysis. If you're
sociologiques intéressante si vous vous
wondering, how can I put it? My
demandez mais comment dire mes
recommendations and implementation of  These are the
préconisations et réalisation de ces de
fortunate ones. If we were to talk about the
cette heureuse si on parlait de la
French situation, for example, what
situation française par exemple que
needs to be done in France? Well, you
faut-il faire en france bien il vous
would expect
prendrez s'attendre de mesures
drastic, difficult measures, which
drastiques difficile qui de toute
obviously include housing, a
évidence vous le logement ou un système
customizable retirement system, or extending
de retraite à la carte ou l'allongement
working hours. Obviously,
la durée du travail de toute évidence
unfortunately, we don't understand. We
malheureusement on ne comprend pas il
need to take a break from
faut prendre servait une pause dans
the evolution of all types of remuneration
l'évolution des rémunérations de toute
because the unfortunate
nature parce que le le malheureux
tax credits following the
crédits d'impôts suite au rapport
Gallois report only cover about a
gallois ne comblent qu'à peu près un
third of the competitiveness gap that
tiers de l'écart de compétitivité qui
exists between our economy and the
existe entre notre économie l'économie
German economy. So the other two-thirds
allemand donc les deux autres tiers
must be found somewhere, perhaps through
doivent bien être trouver quelque part
a pause that is necessary
par proment par une pause qu'il faut
to allow companies to
faire pour permettre aux entreprises de
rebuild their
regonfler leur capacité
self-financing capacity, in particular. In short, there are
d'autofinancement notamment d'un bref ya
a number of measures to take, all
un certain nombre de mesures à prendre
relatively popular,
qui sont toutes relativement populaire
which, over two years, should be implemented
qui pendant deux ans
massively together and
reese massivement tous ensemble doivent
allow us to
permettre de nous permettre
regain a form of
effectivement de retrouver une forme de
confidence and a glimmer of hope.
confiance et un coin de ciel bleu à
Simply, I don't believe that
l'horizon simplement je ne crois pas que
politically, any
politiquement aucun gouvernement
current government, left or right, is
actuellement de gauche ou de droite soit
capable of implementing them. Those that
capable de les mettre en oeuvre qui
remain will inevitably be...  Unpopular
restent seront fatalement impopulaires
as he was, whatever his political stance, whether left-wing
qu'il avait quelles qu'elles soient de
or right-wing, I'll say, is that in this
gauche ou cas soit droite je vais dire
game, I advocate for
à ce jeu je plaide pour
a kind of national unity government
un espèce de gouvernement d'union
of public salvation, representing
national de salut public représentant
people of goodwill from both sides, composed of
regroupant des gens de bonne volonté de
moderate politicians. I know
politiques modérés je connais aussi bien
some technocrats on both the left and the right;
quelques technocrates
they're not all as they say and
ils sont pas tous comme on dit et
without merit, far from it. A
sans intérêt loin de là et qu'un
government would
gouvernement pendant deux ans mettre en
implement all these measures for two years, and then, after
oeuvre toutes ces mesures et puis au
two years, well, that's it, the party's over, so to speak,
bout de deux ans bien coupe sifflé la
the
récréation est terminée si j'ose dire la
political battle resumes. At least we will have brought the
bataille politique reprend au moins on
country back up to speed, and once again, it will
aura remis le le pays à niveau et encore
be tough, it will be a difficult effort.
une fois ça sera rude ce sera un effort
The final word, others don't, but
le mot de la fin d'autres non mais une
once we are faced with situations that are perhaps quite
fois qu'on est face à des situations
paradoxical—we were
peut-être assez assez paradoxal on
talking about individualism earlier,
parlait de l'individualisme tout à
but we say, if I introduce too much
l'heure mais on se dit si je mets trop
individualism, it ends up
d'individualisme et ça finit par
disrupting the economic system. It will
brouiller le système économique un ça va
create massive disorder, and we know very
créer un désordre massif et on sait très
well that the population, faced with
bien que la population face à un
disorder, will choose order rather than...
désordre à choisir à l'ordre plutôt qu'à
Freedom, so it risks hindering
liberté donc ça risque de ramer des
authoritarian regimes as well. The euro,
régimes autoritaires également l'euro
which we've been talking about, we often say is a bit
dont on a parlé on dit souvent d'être un
hasty. Europe is peace, okay,
peu rapidement l'europe c'est la paix ok
maybe, but six months just because
peut-être mais six mois parce que
Europe is peace, because the euro won't mean
l'europe c'est la paix que l'euro se
war. The problem is that
sera pas la guerre je le problème c'est
it pushes some of them towards
que ça pousse un des leurs autour de
nationalism, a return of
nationalisme un retour d'égoïsme
extremely significant selfishness in Europe when we
extrêmement important en europe quand on
see what's happening today, how
voit ce qui se passe aujourd'hui comment
Germans are perceived throughout
sont perçus les allemands dans toute
southern Europe, for good or
l'europe du sud prend des bonnes ou
bad reasons, especially compared to what they had
mauvaises raisons enfin par rapport à ce
five years ago.
qu'ils avaient il ya cinq ans 10 mai
So it doesn't seem to be heading towards
donc ça a pas l'air d'aller vraiment
universal harmony in Europe, this
vers la concorde universelle en europe
thing. So in conclusion, what to
ce ce truc là alors en conclusion que
do, or some ideas?
faire ou quelques quelques idées
I really think we need to become
moi je pense vraiment qu'il faut arriver
aware that
à prendre conscience que
the phenomenal growth of the
l'augmentation phénoménale du secteur
financial sector over the last fifteen
financier depuis depuis une quinzaine
years is something unhealthy. I do
d'années quelque chose de malsain
n't like the term "financial" because it's
j'aime pas le terme financier parce que
not a financial sector that has
c'est pas un secteur financier qui s'est
developed, but a speculative one. It's a financial sector that
développé sa secteur spéculatif c'est un
is indispensable. We need it.  What's
financier est indispensable on en a
needed is that it's full of brilliant people, and
besoin c'est plein de gens brillants et
anyway, even in this whole
de toute façon d'ailleurs même dans tout
system, it's full of
ce système là c'est plein de gens
brilliant people everywhere, but most of them
brillants partout mais dont la plupart
are working to ruin
sont en train de travailler la ruine de
the real economy, the
l'économie réelle de l'économie
industrial economy. Note that we
industrielle de l'économie note on a
need the industrial economy
besoin d'économie industrielle
to realize that this sector is
de prendre conscience que ce secteur-là
not healthy and that it needs to be
n'est pas sain et qu'il faut le
deflated quickly. We are very
dégonfler rapidement wac on en est très
far from that; we continue to consider it
loin on continue à considérer que c'est
almost a solution. There may be
presque une solution peut avoir des
banks that still have this type of
banques qui ont quand même type et leurs
balance sheet over 4, 5, 15 years, which is healthy, and
bilans par 4 5 ans 15 ans est sain et
that we absolutely must preserve all these
qu'il faut absolument préserver tous ces
derivative products, which are
produits dérivés qui ne sont que des
purely speculative products, a kind of
produits purement de spéculation des
casino product that
espèces de produits casino qui met en
endangers the entire economic system.
danger l'ensemble du système économique
Unfortunately, the banking law, which we didn't talk about much earlier,
malheureusement la loi bancaire dont on
but which we can discuss in
tout à l'heure mais on peut parler dans
the media, shows that unfortunately, the
les médias montrent que malheureusement
conclusion is that the system is
la conclusion est que le système n'est
not reformable. I'm sure the whole wheel had to be turned,
pas réformable je suis toute la roue a
but by F1, without a
dû être mais par f1 sans un épisode
painful episode, obviously, but that we are
douloureux évidemment mais qu'on est
condemned to rebuild Liesberg a second
condamné à retaper liesberg une deuxième
time, and perhaps at a cost.  of the system, and that's what's quite
fois et peut-être un coût du système et
frightening, because the banking law, when you
flippant parce que la loi bancaire quand
see the positions on the left, on the right, in the
on voit les positions à gauche à droite
center, will be settled quickly and efficiently.
au centre sera d'être réglée vite fait
We should have returned
bien fait on aurait dû arriver de
to the separation of
nouveau à la séparation des activités
banking activities, which, I remind you, was the
bancaires qui je le rappelle était la
law in France between 1945 and, in practice,
loi en france entre 45 et en pratique
1995. So all we're asking for  And so, it's like
1995 donc tout ce qu'on demande c'est
going back to the banking landscape of 1995, where things weren't
revenir au paysage bancaire dès 1995 où
working too badly. We realize
ça marchait pas trop mal on s'aperçoit
that because it's not possible, we mustn't
que le fait que c'est pas possible il
touch anything, especially since we're not
faut toucher à rien surtout nous ne
limiting the activities or the
limitons pas les des activités ni
traders' remuneration. Okay, very well,
rémunération des traders ok très bien
you know, since there's no
vous comme ya pas de pression
strong popular pressure on this point, the bomb
populaire un forte sur ce point la bombe
is doomed. Indeed, as
en est condamné en effet comme l'a dit
Olivier Delamarche said two weeks ago, we're
olivier delamarche il ya quinze jours à
all Cypriot. Well, that's what's in
être tous chypriote bien c'est ça qui
front of us. It's a
est un qui est devant nous bon c'est
shame because with a little
dommage parce que avec un peu
collective intelligence and a little
d'intelligence collective à un peu de
goodwill, we could undoubtedly have made much more
bonne volonté on aurait sans doute pu
efficient decisions. And what
beaucoup plus efficiente et moi ce qui
worries me is that sometimes I think, if we had randomly selected
ce qui m'inquiète c'est que des fois je
100 people, held a mini-
100 personnes on aurait fait une mini
assembly to present the problems,
assemblée pour présenter les problèmes
they would have been able to make decisions
il arriverait à prendre des décisions
because people, individually, aren't
parce que les gens individuellement et
stupid, aren't completely
sont pas stupides sont pas complètement
irresponsible. And when the
irresponsable et quand le système
political system today can no longer manage,
politique aujourd'hui n'y arrive plus
undoubtedly also due to short-termism,
sans doute aussi par court termisme sans
undoubtedly also due to a lack of sanctions,
doute aussi par manque de sanctions sans
undoubtedly also because  When you enter
doute aussi parce que quand on entre en
politics at 35 and are 70, you'll
politique à 35 ans et contient 70 on
always be there, inevitably. This
sera toujours là en bas forcément ça
forces you to act in a certain way that isn't at
oblige à agir d'une certaine façon qui
all the one we'd expect, the one we'd
n'est pas du tout celle qui est qui qui
use.
serait celle qu'on qu'on emploie récit
We were only there for five years, this short-
on n'était là que pour cinq ans le court
termism. We really need to say something about it.
termisme il faut effectivement dire un
I mean, the effects are absolutely
mot je veux dire des effets absolument
disastrous. We've completely forgotten the
désastreux on a complètement oublié le
long term that should govern
temps long qui devrait régir les
the economy. This is evident in
l'économie ça se voit au travers
countless phenomena.
d'innombrables phénomène les comptes
Quarterly accounts mean we'll have
trimestriels veut dire on aura des
monthly accounts one day, or a
comptes mensuels un jour ou un décompte
daily count. I'd even say it's
quotidien je diront d'ailleurs elle est
especially appreciated. They're
surtout apprécié prêteront ils sont
capable of doing daily accounts,
capables de faire des comptes quotidien
having hourly counts, I don't know. It's a
avoir décompte horaire je ne sais pas à
caricature, but it's if we
face caricature mais donc c'est si on
're in a system that's going
est dans un système qui devient
completely crazy
complètement fou
and that doesn't generate the
et qui n'engendre pas d'ailleurs le
desire to invest in
désir d'investir de faire de la
research and development, the mother
recherche développement maire de
of
l'innovation une des mères de
innovation. But this is the main thing. So all this means that this
l'innovation mais cela on la principale
short-termism, to which
court termisme que auquel sacrifient les
French companies are currently sacrificing their
entreprises françaises actuellement les
research and
grandes entreprises lanto de recherche
development, is decreasing compared to their
développement diminue par rapport à leur
figures.  Business could allow for
chiffre d'affaires pourrait en permettre
the release of quarterly financial results that are
la lah des résultats financiers
slightly more attractive than expected, so
peu plus séduisant que ceux prévus donc
they are doing what is necessary to release them, and
ils font ce qu'il faut sortir et
I believe it is up to the government, through
je crois que c'est au gouvernement par
measures itself based on a
des mesures elle même basée sur un temps
long-term perspective, to set an example and encourage
long de donner l'exemple et d'entraîner
businesses to follow suit. But at this
de nouveaux les entreprises mais à ce
stage, it would be necessary to change the culture
stade il faudrait il changer la culture
of all financial analysts in
de tous les analystes financiers des
rating agencies. Well, that won't happen overnight, especially since
agences de notation bon ça ne se fera
the phenomenon originated in the
pas en un jour d'autant que le phénomène
United States, and they are the ones who
est partie des états unis et que c'est
hold, to some extent, the
eux qui tiennent un petit peu dans ce
levers of power in this area—
domaine les leviers du pouvoir
how to put it, intellectual power. The
comment dire intellectuelle et l'os le
problem is that it's a real
problème c'est que c'est une sacrée
pair of nations in our
paire nation de notre fonctionnement
societal functioning. Inevitably, when we deregulated
sociétal forcément quand on a dérégulé
in the 80s, if you deregulate, it
dans les années 80 si vous dérégulé pour
becomes a law of the jungle,
venir quelque part une loi de la jungle
and therefore, to some extent, you are forced
et donc quelque part vous êtes obligés
to be short-termist because if you
d'être court termiste parce que si vous
are long-termist when facing
êtes long termiste face à des
competitors who are
entreprises des concurrents qui sont
short-termist, you will lose. So
court termiste vous allez perdre donc
obviously, you have a development of
évidemment vous avez un développement de
this short-term vision, therefore
cette vision à court terme donc de
wanting to make profits in the very short
vouloir faire des profits à très court
term. In the financial sector, you
terme dans le secteur financier vous
have ways of doing so.  Very short-
avez des moyens d'en faire un très court
term gains that will sink the company in five
terme qui couleront la boîte à cinq ans
or ten years, but that's no longer your
ou à 10 ans mais c'est plus votre
problem since you yourselves are
problème puisque vous êtes vous mêmes
managers who have been in
dirigeants qu elle est restée trois
office for three or four years and are loaded with stock
quatre années en poste et gavés de stock
options, which are therefore a kind of
options qui sont donc une espèce de de
enormous bet on the
paris faramineux sur l'évolution de la
stock market's performance and therefore on what analysts
bourse et donc 2 ce que les analystes
will think of your stock. So this
vont penser de votre action donc ce
system is unhealthy, and it's sad
système là est malsain et c'est triste
because there are plenty of simple measures
parce que il ya plein de mesures simples
that could be taken without
qu'on pourrait prendre sans difficultés
major difficulties with a little courage and
majeures avec un petit peu de courage et
a little understanding of what's going on.
un petit peu de compréhension de ce qui
Why is it that if I make a
se passe pourquoi si je fais un profit
financial profit in 15 minutes or in fifteen years, it's the same? It's still
financier en 15 minutes ou en quinze ans
crazy! Why is it that if I join
même fou pourquoi si j'arrive dans une
a company today I can
dans une entreprise aujourd'hui je peux
vote at the general meeting tomorrow,
voter l'assemblée générale demain
why will my vote tomorrow have the same, or even the
pourquoi ma voix demain aura le même
same weight, as a shareholder
voit pas le même poids qu'un actionnaire
who has been there for 15 years? We could
qui sera là depuis 15 ans on pourrait
change that! Why do we count
changer ça pourquoi est-ce qu'on compte
the shares that have continued to trade on the stock exchange?
les actions ont continué à la bourse
Why does
pourquoi tous les millionièmes de
the value of the
seconde la valeur de l'action de
company's stock change every millionth of a second? You have to be
l'entreprise change mais faut être
crazy to believe that!  You could very well have just one
malade vous pourriez très bien avoir une
value per day, at least that would
seule valeur déjà par jour au moins déjà
eliminate all the speculation. Let's
ça enlèverait toute la spéculation on va
say 20 other
dire que 20 autres à des blagues
daily jokes that serve absolutely no purpose.
quotidienne qui ne sert strictement à
Who can justify a
rien qui peut justifier que la valeur
company's value fluctuating every
d'une entreprise varie tout les
millisecond? It's
millisecondes maintenant enfin c'est du
madness, and we could do this kind of thing.
délire et ces trucs là on pourrait le
95% of people agree, if
faire 95% des gens sont d'accord si
not 100%, we don't know, but
c'est pas 100% on ne le sait pas mais
it's dramatic. It's the
c'est dramatique c'est déjà les mesures
simple measures that help, we do them because we don't do the
simples qui aident on le fait parce que
complicated ones either.
les mesures compliqué on les fait pas
People do nothing, Father
non plus les gens ne fait rien père
Resto. And look, Liesberg
resto ainsi et regardons liesberg
was calmly approaching us. That will
s'approchait tranquillement de nous ce
be the last word, perhaps. Olivier
sera le mot de la fin peut-être olivier
Delamarche, a last word? Yes, we've
delamarche un dernier mot oui on est
gone from governing is about planning to
passé de gouverner c'est prévoir
governing is not about seeing your next
gouverner c'est pas voir sa prochaine
election.
élection
[Music]
[Musique]